<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<test-set>
	<topic t_id="1" t_name="AIDS">
		<reading-test r_id="1">
			<doc d_id="1">
Annie Lennox Why I am an HIVAIDS activistI'm going to share with you the story as to how I have become an HIV/AIDS campaigner. And this is the name of my campaign, SING Campaign. In November of 2003 I was invited to take part in the launch of Nelson Mandela's 46664 Foundation. That is his HIV/AIDS foundation. And 46664 is the number that Mandela had when he was imprisoned in Robben Island. And that's me with Youssou N'Dour, onstage, having the time of my life. The next day, all the artists were invited to join Mandela in Robben Island, where he was he was going to give a conference to the world's press, standing in front of his former prison cell. You can see the bars of the window there. It was quite a momentous occasion for all of us. In that moment in time, Mandela told the world's press that there was a virtual genocide taking place in his country, that post-apartheid Rainbow Nation, a thousand were dying on a daily basis, and that the front line victims, the most vulnerable of all, were women and children.This was a huge impact on my mind, because I am a woman, and I am a mother, and I hadn't realized that the HIV/AIDS pandemic was directly affecting women in such a way. And so I committed -- when I left South Africa, when I left Capetown, I told myself, "This is going to be something that I have to talk about. I have to serve." And so, subsequently, I participated in every single 46664 event that I could take part in and gave news conferences, interviews, talking and using my platform as a musician, with my commitment to Mandela, out of respect for the tremendous, unbelievable work that he had done. Everyone one in the world respects Nelson Mandela. Everyone reveres Nelson Mandela. But do they all know about what has been taking place in South Africa, his country, the country that had one of the highest incidents of transmission of the virus? I think that if I went out into the street now, and I told people what was happening there, they would be shocked.I was very very fortunate, a couple of years later, to have met Zackie Achmat, the founder of Treatment Action Campaign, an incredible campaigner and activist. I met him at a 46664 event. He was wearing a t-shirt like the one I wear now. This is a tool. This tells you I am in solidarity with people who have HIV, people who are living with HIV. And in a way, because of the stigma, by wearing this t-shirt, I say, "Yes, we can talk about this issue. It doesn't have to be in the closet." I became a member of Treatment Action Campaign, and I'm very proud to be a member of that incredible organization. It's a grassroots campaign with 80 percent membership being women, most of whom are HIV-positive. They work in the field. They have tremendous outreach to the people who are living directly with the effects of the virus. They have education programs. They bring out the issues of stigma. It's quite extraordinary what they do. And yes, my SING Campaign has supported Treatment Action Campaign in the way that I have tried to raise awareness and to try to also raise funds. A lot of the funding that I have managed to raise has gone directly to Treatment Action Campaign and the incredible work that they do, and are still continuing to do, in South Africa.So this is my SING Campaign. SING Campaign is basically just me and about three or four wonderful people who help to support me. I've traveled all over the world in the last two and a half years. I went to about 12 different countries. Here I am in Oslo in Norway, getting a nice, fat check, singing in Hong Kong, trying to get people to raise money. In Johannesburg, I had the opportunity to play to a mainly white, middle-class South African audience who ended up in tears, because I use film clips that really touch the heart, the whole nature, of this terrible tragedy that is taking place, that people are tending to avoid, because they are fatigued, and they really don't quite know what the solutions are. Aaron Motsoaledi, the current health minister, attended that concert, and I had an opportunity to meet with him, and he gave his absolute commitment to try to making a change, which is absolutely necessary. This is in the Scottish Parliament. I've subsequently become an envoy for Scotland and HIV. And I was showing them my experiences and trying to, again, raise awareness. And once again, in Edinburgh, with the wonderful African Children's Choir who I simply adore. And it's children like this, many of whom have been orphaned because of their family being affected by the AIDS virus.I'm sitting here in New York with Michel Sidibe. He's the director of UNAIDS. And I'm very honored by the fact that Michel invited me, only a few months ago, to become a UNAIDS ambassador. And in this way, I've been strengthening my platform and broadening my outreach. The message that UNAIDS are currently sending out to the world is that we would like to see the virtual elimination of the transmission of the virus from mother to child by 2015. It's a very ambitious goal, but we believe it can be achieved with political will. This can happen.And here I am with a pregnant woman who is HIV positive, and we're smiling, both of us are smiling, because we're very confident, because we know that that young woman is receiving treatment so her life can be extended to take care of the baby she's about to give birth to. And her baby will receive PMTCT, which will mean that that baby can be born free of the virus. Now that is prevention at the very beginning of life. It's one way to start looking at intervention with the AIDS pandemic.Now, I just would like to finish off to tell you the little story about Avelile. This is Avelile. She goes with me wherever I go. I tell her story to everyone, because she represents one of millions of HIV/AIDS orphans. Avelile's mother had HIV virus. She died from AIDS-related illness. Avelile had the virus. She was born with the virus. And here she is at seven years old, weighing no more than a one year-old baby. At this point in her life, she's suffering with full-blown AIDS and had pneumonia. We met her in a hospital in the Eastern Cape and spent a whole afternoon with her -- an adorable child. The doctors and nurses were phenomenal. They put her on very special nutritious diet and took great care of her. And we didn't know when we left the hospital -- because we filmed her story -- we didn't know if she was going to survive. So, it was obviously ... it was a very emotional encounter and left us feeling very resonant with this direct experience, this one child, you know, that story. Five months later, we went back to South Africa to meet Avelile again. And I'm getting -- the hairs on my -- I don't know if you can see the hairs on my arms. They're standing up, because I know what I'm going to show you. This is the transformation that took place. Isn't it extraordinary?(Applause)That round of applause is actually for the doctors and nurses of the hospital who took care of Avelile. And I take it that you appreciate that kind of transformation. So, I would like to say to you, each one in the audience, if you feel that every mother and every child in the world has the right to have access to good nutrition and good medical care, and you believe that the Millennium Development Goals, specifically five and six, should be absolutely committed to by all governments around the world -- especially in sub-Saharan Africa -- could you please stand up. I think that's fair to say, it's almost everyone in the hall.Thank you very much.(Applause)
			</doc>
				<q  q_id="1" >
					<q_str>What event caused Annie Lennox to commit herself to the fight against AIDS?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >the imprisonment of Nelson Mandela at Robben Island</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >the closing ceremony of Nelson Mandela's Foundation</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >the meeting with Youssou N'Dour</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >the racial segregation in South Africa</answer>
					<answer a_id='5'  correct="Yes">Nelson Mandela's conference to the world press</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="2" >
					<q_str>Who is the founder of the SING campaign?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >Nelson Mandela</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >Youssou N'Dour</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >Michel Sidibe</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >Zackie Achmat</answer>
					<answer a_id='5'  correct="Yes">Annie Lennox</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="3" >
					<q_str>What is Nelson Mandela's country of origin?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >Norway</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >Scotland</answer>
					<answer a_id='3'  correct="Yes">South Africa</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >United States</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >Namibia</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="4" >
					<q_str>What did Nelson Mandela say at the press conference?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1'  correct="Yes">thousands of people were being wiped out by AIDS</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >thousands of people were having the time of their life</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >thousands of women were having many children</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >thousands of people were imprisoned</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >thousands of people were leaving South Africa</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="5" >
					<q_str>What is Annie Lennox's profession?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >mother</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >nurse in a hospital</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >farmer</answer>
					<answer a_id='4'  correct="Yes">musician</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >dancer</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="6" >
					<q_str>What is Annie Lennox's opinion about Nelson Mandela? </q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >she criticises him</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >she hates him</answer>
					<answer a_id='3'  correct="Yes">she esteems him</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >she is scared by him</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >she is offended by him</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="7" >
					<q_str>In which European cities has Annie Lennox performed? </q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >London and Paris</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >Oslo and Hong Kong</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >Edinburgh and Johannesburg</answer>
					<answer a_id='4'  correct="Yes">Edinburgh and Oslo</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >Hong Kong and Johannesburg</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="8" >
					<q_str>What is the objective of UNAIDS?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >to make an agreement with the health minister</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >to give a concert with the African Children's Choir</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >to avoid HIV-positive women becoming pregnant</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >to extend UNAIDS's outreach</answer>
					<answer a_id='5'  correct="Yes">to avoid HIV being transmitted from mother to child</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="9" >
					<q_str>Why is Avelile suffering from AIDS?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >because she contracted the virus in hospital</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >because she was underweight</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >because she had pneumonia</answer>
					<answer a_id='4'  correct="Yes">because her mother transmitted the virus to her</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >because she is an orphan</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="10" >
					<q_str>Do people agree that governments should be committed to fighting AIDS?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1'  correct="Yes">definitely yes</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >definitely no</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >unknown</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >sometimes</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >only one person agrees</answer>
				</q>
		</reading-test>
		<reading-test r_id="2">
			<doc d_id="2">
Bono's call to action for AfricaWell, as Alexander Graham Bell famously said on his first successful telephone call, "Hello, is that Domino's Pizza?" (Laughter) I just really want to thank you very much. As another famous man, Jerry Garcia, said, "What a strange, long trip." And he should have said, "What a strange, long trip it's about to become." At this very moment, you are viewing my upper half. My lower half is appearing at a different conference -- (Laughter) in a different country. You can, it turns out, be in two places at once. But still, I'm sorry I can't be with you in person. I'll explain at another time.And though I'm a rock star, I just want to assure you that none of my wishes will include a hot tub. But what really turns me on about technology is not just the ability to get more songs on mp3 players. The revolution -- this revolution -- is much bigger than that. I hope, I believe. What turns me on about the digital age, what excited me personally, is that you have closed the gap between dreaming and doing. You see, it used to be that if you wanted to make a record of a song, you needed a studio and a producer. Now, you need a laptop. If you wanted to make a film, you needed a mass of equipment and a Hollywood budget. Now, you need a camera that fits in your palm, and a couple of bucks for a blank DVD. Imagination has been decoupled from the old constraints. And that really, really excites me. I'm excited when I glimpse that kind of thinking writ large.What I would like to see is idealism decoupled from all constraints. Political, economic, psychological, whatever. The geopolitical world has got a lot to learn from the digital world. From the ease with which you swept away obstacles that no one knew could even be budged. And that's actually what I'd like to talk about today. First, though, I should probably explain why, and how, I got to this place. It's a journey that started 20 years ago. You may remember that song, "We Are the World," or, "Do They Know It's Christmas?" Band Aid, Live Aid. Another very tall, grizzled rock star, my friend Sir Bob Geldof, issued a challenge to "feed the world." It was a great moment, and it utterly changed my life. That summer, my wife, Ali, and myself went to Ethiopia. We went on the quiet to see for ourselves what was going on. We lived in Ethiopia for a month, working at an orphanage. The children had a name for me. They called me, "The girl with the beard."(Laughter)Don't ask. Anyway, we found Africa to be a magical place. Big skies, big hearts, big, shining continent. Beautiful, royal people. Anybody who ever gave anything to Africa got a lot more back. Ethiopia didn't just blow my mind; it opened my mind. Anyway, on our last day at this orphanage a man handed me his baby and said, "Would you take my son with you?" He knew, in Ireland, that his son would live, and that in Ethiopia, his son would die. It was the middle of that awful famine. Well, I turned him down. And it was a funny kind of sick feeling, but I turned him down. And it's a feeling I can't ever quite forget. And in that moment, I started this journey.In that moment, I became the worst thing of all: I became a rock star with a cause. Except this isn't the cause, is it? Six and a half thousand Africans dying every single day from AIDS -- a preventable, treatable disease -- for lack of drugs we can get in any pharmacy. That's not a cause. That's an emergency. 11 million AIDS orphans in Africa, 20 million by the end of the decade. That's not a cause. That's an emergency. Today, every day, 9,000 more Africans will catch HIV because of stigmatization and lack of education. That's not a cause. That's an emergency. So what we're talking about here is human rights. The right to live like a human. The right to live, period. And what we're facing in Africa is an unprecedented threat to human dignity and equality.The next thing I'd like to be clear about is what this problem is, and what this problem isn't. Because this is not all about charity. This is about justice. Really. This is not about charity. This is about justice. That's right. And that's too bad, because we're very good at charity. Americans, like Irish people, are good at it. Even the poorest neighborhoods give more than they can afford. We like to give, and we give a lot. Look at the response to the tsunami, it's inspiring. But justice is a tougher standard than charity. You see, Africa makes a fool of our idea of justice. It makes a farce of our idea of equality. It mocks our pieties. It doubts our concern. It questions our commitment. Because there is no way we can look at what's happening in Africa, and if we're honest, conclude that it would ever be allowed to happen anywhere else.As you heard in the film, anywhere else, not here. Not here, not in America, not in Europe. In fact, a head of state that you're all familiar with admitted this to me. And it's really true. There is no chance this kind of hemorrhaging of human life would be accepted anywhere else other than Africa. Africa is a continent in flames. And deep down, if we really accepted that Africans were equal to us, we would all do more to put the fire out. We're standing around with watering cans, when what we really need is the fire brigade.You see, it's not as dramatic as the tsunami. It's crazy, really, when you think about it. Does stuff have to look like an action movie these days to exist in the front of our brain? The slow extinguishing of countless lives is just not dramatic enough, it would appear. Catastrophes that we can avert are not as interesting as ones we could avert. Funny, that. Anyway, I believe that that kind of thinking offends the intellectual rigor in this room. Six and a half thousand people dying a day in Africa may be Africa's crisis, but the fact that it's not on the nightly news, that we in Europe, or you in America, are not treating it like an emergency -- I want to argue with you tonight that that's our crisis. I want to argue that though Africa is not the front line in the war against terror, it could be soon. Every week, religious extremists take another African village. They're attempting to bring order to chaos. Well, why aren't we?Poverty breeds despair. We know this. Despair breeds violence. We know this. In turbulent times, isn't it cheaper, and smarter, to make friends out of potential enemies than to defend yourself against them later? The war against terror is bound up in the war against poverty. And I didn't say that. Colin Powell said that. Now when the military are telling us that this is a war that cannot be won by military might alone, maybe we should listen. There's an opportunity here, and it's real. It's not spin. It's not wishful thinking. The problems facing the developing world afford us in the developed world a chance to re-describe ourselves to the world. We will not only transform other people's lives, but we will also transform the way those other lives see us. And that might be smart in these nervous, dangerous times.Don't you think that on a purely commercial level, that anti-retroviral drugs are great advertisements for Western ingenuity and technology? Doesn't compassion look well on us? And let's cut the crap for a second. In certain quarters of the world, brand EU, brand USA, is not at its shiniest. The neon sign is fizzing and cracking. Someone's put a brick through the window. The regional branch managers are getting nervous. Never before have we in the west been so scrutinized. Our values: do we have any? Our credibility? These things are under attack around the world. Brand USA could use some polishing. And I say that as a fan, you know? As a person who buys the products. But think about it. More anti-retrovirals make sense. But that's just the easy part, or ought to be.But equality for Africa -- that's a big, expensive idea. You see, the scale of the suffering numbs us into a kind of indifference. What on earth can we all do about this? Well, much more than we think. We can't fix every problem, but the ones we can, I want to argue, we must. And because we can, we must. This is the straight truth, the righteous truth. It is not a theory. The fact is that ours is the first generation that can look disease and extreme poverty in the eye, look across the ocean to Africa, and say this, and mean it. We do not have to stand for this. A whole continent written off -- we do not have to stand for this.(Applause)And let me say this without a trace of irony -- before I back it up to a bunch of ex-hippies. Forget the '60s. We can change the world. I can't, you can't, as individuals, but we can change the world. I really believe that, the people in this room. Look at the Gates Foundation. They've done incredible stuff, unbelievable stuff. But working together, we can actually change the world. We can turn the inevitable outcomes, and transform the quality of life for millions of lives who look and feel rather like us, when you're up close. I'm sorry to laugh here, but you do look so different than you did in Haight-Ashbury in the '60s.(Laughter)But I want to argue that this is the moment that you are designed for. It is the flowering of the seeds you planted in earlier, headier days. Ideas that you gestated in your youth. This is what excites me. This room was born for this moment, is really what I want to say to you tonight. Most of you started out wanting to change the world, didn't you? Most of you did, the digital world. Well, now, actually because of you, it is possible to change the physical world. It's a fact. Economists confirm it, and they know much more than I do. So why, then, are we not pumping our fists into the air? Probably because when we admit we can do something about it, we've got to do something about it. It is a pain in the arse. This equality business is actually a pain in the arse. But for the first time in history, we have the technology, we have the know-how, we have the cash, we have the life-saving drugs.Do we have the will? I hope this is obvious, but I'm not a hippie. And I'm not really one for the warm, fuzzy feeling. I do not have flowers in my hair. Actually, I come from punk rock. The Clash wore big army boots, not sandals. But I know toughness when I see it. And for all the talk of peace and love on the West Coast, there was muscle to the movement that started out here. You see, idealism detached from action is just a dream. But idealism allied with pragmatism, with rolling up your sleeves and making the world bend a bit, is very exciting. It's very real. It's very strong. And it's very present in a crowd like you.Last year at DATA, this organization I helped set up, we launched a campaign to summon this spirit in the fight against AIDS and extreme poverty. We're calling it the ONE Campaign. It's based on our belief that the action of one person can change a lot, but the actions of many coming together as one can change the world. Well, we feel that now is the time to prove we're right. There are moments in history when civilization redefines itself. We believe this is one. We believe that this could be the time when the world finally decides that the wanton loss of life in Africa is just no longer acceptable. This could be the time that we finally get serious about changing the future for most people who live on planet Earth.Momentum has been building. Lurching a little, but it's building. This year is a test for us all, especially the leaders of the G8 nations, who really are on the line here, with all the world in history watching. I have been, of late, disappointed with the Bush Administration. They started out with such promise on Africa. They made some really great promises, and actually have fulfilled a lot of them. But some of them they haven't. They don't feel the push from the ground, is the truth. But my disappointment has much more perspective when I talk to American people, and I hear their worries about the deficit, and the fiscal well-being of their country. I understand that. But there's much more push from the ground than you'd think, if we got organized.What I try to communicate, and you can help me if you agree, is that aid for Africa is just great value for money at a time when America really needs it. Putting it in the crassest possible terms, the investment reaps huge returns. Not only in lives saved, but in goodwill, stability and security that we'll gain. So this is what I hope that you will do, if I could be so bold, and not have it deducted from my number of wishes.(Laughter)What I hope is that beyond individual merciful acts, that you will tell the politicians to do right by Africa, by America and by the world. Give them permission, if you like, to spend their political capital and your financial capital, your national purse on saving the lives of millions of people. That's really what I would like you to do. Because we also need your intellectual capital: your ideas, your skills, your ingenuity. And you, at this conference, are in a unique position. Some of the technologies we've been talking about, you invented them, or at least revolutionized the way that they're used. Together you have changed the zeitgeist from analog to digital, and pushed the boundaries. And we'd like you to give us that energy. Give us that kind of dreaming, that kind of doing.As I say, there're two things on the line here. There's the continent Africa. But there's also our sense of ourselves. People are starting to figure this out. Movements are springing up. Artists, politicians, pop stars, priests, CEOs, NGOs, mothers' unions, student unions. A lot of people are getting together, and working under this umbrella I told you about earlier, the ONE Campaign. I think they just have one idea in their mind, which is, where you live in the world, should not determine whether you live in the world.(Applause)History, like God, is watching what we do. When the history books get written I think our age will be remembered for three things. Really, it's just three things this whole age will be remembered for. The digital revolution, yes. The war against terror, yes. And what we did or did not do to put out the fires in Africa. Some say we can't afford to. I say we can't afford not to. Thank you, thank you very much.(Applause)Okay, my three wishes. The ones that TED has offered to grant. You see, if this is true, and I believe it is, that the digital world you all created has uncoupled the creative imagination from the physical constraints of matter. This should be a piece of piss.(Laughter)I should add that this started out as a much longer list of wishes. Most of them impossible, some of them impractical and one or two of them certainly immoral.(Laughter)This business, it gets to be addictive, you know what I mean, when somebody else is picking up the tab. Anyway, here's number one. I wish for you to help build a social movement of more than one million American activists for Africa. That is my first wish. I believe it's possible. A few minutes ago, I talked about all the citizens' campaigns that are springing up. You know, there's lots out there. And with this one campaign as our umbrella, my organization, DATA, and other groups, have been tapping into the energy and the enthusiasm that's out there from Hollywood into the heartland of America. We know there's more than enough energy to power this movement. We just need your help in making it happen.We want all of you here, church America, corporate America, Microsoft America, Apple America, Coke America, Pepsi America, nerd America, noisy America. We can't afford to be cool and sit this one out. I do believe if we build a movement that's one million Americans strong, we're not going to be denied. We will have the ear of Congress. We'll be the first page in Condi Rice's briefing book, and right into the Oval Office. If there's one million Americans -- and I really know this -- who are ready to make phone calls, who are ready to be on email. I am absolutely sure that we can actually change the course of history, literally, for the continent of Africa. Anyway, so I'd like your help in getting that signed up. I know John Gage and Sun Microsystems are already on board for this, but there's lots of you we'd like to talk to.Right, my second wish, number two. I would like one media hit for every person on the planet who is living on less than one dollar a day. That's one billion media hits. Could be on Google, could be on AOL. Steve Case, Larry, Sergey -- they've done a lot already. It could be NBC. It could be ABC. Actually we're talking to ABC today about the Oscars. We have a film, produced by Jon Kamen at Radical Media. But you know, we want, we need some airtime for our ideas. We need to get the math, we need to get the statistics out to the American people. I really believe that old Truman line, that if you give the American people the facts, they'll do the right thing. And, the other thing that's important, is that this is not Sally Struthers. This has to be described as an adventure, not a burden.(Video): One by one they step forward, a nurse, a teacher, a homemaker, and lives are saved. The problem is enormous. Every three seconds one person dies. Another three seconds, one more. The situation is so desperate in parts of Africa, Asia, even America that aid groups, just as they did for the tsunami are uniting as one, acting as one. We can beat extreme poverty, starvation, AIDS. But we need your help. One more person, letter, voice will mean the difference between life and death for millions of people. Please join us by working together. Americans have an unprecedented opportunity. We can make history. We can start to make poverty history. One, by one, by one. Please visit ONE at this address. We're not asking for your money. We're asking for your voice.Bono: All right. I wish for TED to truly show the power of information. Its power to rewrite the rules and transform lives, by connecting every hospital, health clinic and school in one African country. And I would like it to be Ethiopia. I believe we can connect every school in Ethiopia, every health clinic, every hospital. We can connect to the Internet. That is my wish, my third wish. I think it's possible. I think we have the money and brains in the room to do that. And that would be a mind-blowing wish to come true. I've been to Ethiopia, as I said earlier. It's actually where it all started for me. The idea that the Internet, which changed all of our lives, can transform a country -- and a continent that has hardly made it to analog, let alone digital -- blows my mind. But it didn't start out that way.The first long-distance line from Boston to New York was used in 1885 on the phone. It was just nine years later that Addis Ababa was connected by phone to Harare, which is 500 kilometers away. Since then, not that much has changed. The average waiting time to get a land line in Ethiopia is actually about seven or eight years. But wireless technology wasn't dreamt up then. Anyway, I'm Irish, and as you can see, I know how important talking is. Communication is very important for Ethiopia -- will transform the country. Nurses getting better training, pharmacists being able to order supplies, doctors sharing their expertise in all aspects of medicine. It's a very, very good idea to get them wired. And that is my third and final wish for you at the TED conference. Thank you very much once again.
			</doc>
				<q  q_id="1" >
					<q_str>What is Bono's attitude towards the digital age?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >sorrow</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >sadness</answer>
					<answer a_id='3'  correct="Yes">enthusiasm</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >indifference</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >anger</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="2" >
					<q_str>Name a founder of Band Aid.</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >Bono Vox</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >Ali Hewson</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >Jon Anderson</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >Geoffrey Downes</answer>
					<answer a_id='5'  correct="Yes">Robert Frederick Zenon Geldof</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="3" >
					<q_str>Which African country did Bono Vox visit?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >Somalia</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >Horn of Africa</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >Sudan</answer>
					<answer a_id='4'  correct="Yes">Abyssinia</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >Eritrea</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="4" >
					<q_str>What is Paul David Hewson's occupation?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1'  correct="Yes">rock star</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >tourist guide </answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >chef</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >programmer</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >film director</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="5" >
					<q_str>What was the purpose of Band Aid?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >to raise money to end poverty</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >to raise money for cancer research </answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >to raise money for a children's hospital</answer>
					<answer a_id='4'  correct="Yes">to raise money for famine relief </answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >to raise money to eliminate AIDS</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="6" >
					<q_str>Where does "The girl with the beard" live?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >Ethiopia</answer>
					<answer a_id='2'  correct="Yes">Ireland</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >Africa</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >America</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >United States</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="7" >
					<q_str>Why do people in Africa die of AIDS, according to Bono?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >because of the extreme poverty</answer>
					<answer a_id='2'  correct="Yes">because of the lack of drugs</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >because of the lack of money</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >because of the indifference of American people</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >because of the political indifference</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="8" >
					<q_str>In what year was the capital city of Ethiopia connected by phone to Harare?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >1885</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >1858</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >1948</answer>
					<answer a_id='4'  correct="Yes">1894</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >1984</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="9" >
					<q_str>Who is one of the founders of "Debt, AIDS, Trade in Africa"?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1'  correct="Yes">Bono Vox</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >Bob Geldof</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >Midge Ure</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >Chad Gracey</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >Chad Taylor</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="10" >
					<q_str>Name one reason why it is important to connect Ethiopia to the internet, according to Bono.</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1'  correct="Yes">better professional education for nurses</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >better wireless technology</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >better Hollywood budget</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >better connections to New York</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >better conditions in orphanages</answer>
				</q>
		</reading-test>
		<reading-test r_id="3">
			<doc d_id="3">
Elizabeth Pisani: Sex, drugs and HIV -- let's get rational"People do stupid things. That's what spreads HIV." This was a headline in a U.K. newspaper, The Guardian, not that long ago. I'm curious -- show of hands -- who agrees with it? Well, one or two brave souls.This is actually a direct quote from an epidemiologist who's been in field of HIV for 15 years, worked on four continents, and you're looking at her.And I am now going to argue that this is only half true. People do get HIV because they do stupid things, but most of them are doing stupid things for perfectly rational reasons. Now, "rational" is the dominant paradigm in public health. And if you put your public health nerd glasses on, you'll see that if we give people the information that they need about what's good for them and what's bad for them, if you give them the services that they can use to act on that information, and a little bit of motivation, people will make rational decisions and live long and healthy lives. Wonderful.That's slightly problematic for me because I work in HIV, and though I'm sure you all know that HIV is about poverty and gender inequality, and if you were at TED '07, it's about coffee prices; actually, HIV's about sex and drugs. And if there are two things that make human beings a little bit irrational, they are erections and addiction.(Laughter)So, let's start with what's rational for an addict. Now, I remember speaking to an Indonesian friend of mine, Frankie. We were having lunch, and he was telling me about when he was in jail in Bali for a drug injection. And it was someone's birthday, and they had very kindly smuggled some heroin in to the jail, and he was very generously sharing it out with all of his colleagues. And so everyone lined up, all the smackheads in a row. And the guy whose birthday it was filled up the fit, and he went down and started injecting people. So he injects the first guy, and then he's wiping the needle on his shirt, and he injects the next guy. And Frankie said, "I'm number 22 in line, and I can see the needle coming down towards me, and there is blood all over the place. It's getting blunter and blunter. And a small part of my brain is thinking, 'That is so gross and really dangerous,' but most of my brain is thinking, 'Please let there be some smack left by the time it gets to me. Please let there be some left.'" And then, telling me this story, Frankie said, "You know, god, drugs really make you stupid."And, you know, you can't fault him for accuracy, but, actually, Frankie, at that time, was a heroin addict, and he was in jail. So his choice was either to accept that dirty needle or not to get high. And if there's one place you really want to get high, it's when you're in jail.But I'm a scientist, and I don't like to make data out of anecdotes, so let's look at some data. We talked to 600 drug addicts in three cities in Indonesia, and we said, "Well, do you know how you get HIV?" "Oh yeah. By sharing needles." I mean, nearly 100 percent. Yeah, by sharing needles. And, "Do you know where you can get a clean needle at a price you can afford to avoid that?" "Oh yeah." 100 percent. "We're smackheads; we know where to get clean needles." "So are you carrying a needle?" We're actually interviewing people on the street, in the places where they're hanging out and taking drugs. "Are you carrying clean needles?" One in four, maximum. So no surprises then that the proportion that actually used clean needles every time they injected in the last week is just about one in 10, and the other nine in 10 are sharing.So you've got this massive mismatch. Everyone knows that if they share they're going to get HIV, but they're all sharing anyway. So what's that about? Is it like you get a better high if you share or something? We asked that to a junkie and they're like, "Are you nuts? You don't want to share a needle anymore than you want to share a toothbrush even with someone you're sleeping with. There's just an ick factor there. No, no. We share needles because we don't want to go to jail." So, in Indonesia at this time, if you were carrying a needle, and the cops rounded you up, they could put you into jail. And that changes the equation slightly, doesn't it. Because your choice now is either, I use my own needle now, or I could share a needle now and get a disease that's going to possibly kill me 10 years from now, or I could use my own needle now and go to jail tomorrow. And while junkies think that it's a really bad idea to expose themselves to HIV, they think it's a much worse idea to spend the next year in jail, where they'll probably end up in Frankie's situation and expose themselves to HIV anyway. So suddenly, it becomes perfectly rational to share needles.Now, let's look at it from a policy maker's point of view. This is a really easy problem. For once, your incentives are aligned. We've got what's rational for public health. You want people to use clean needles, and junkies want to use clean needles. So we could make this problem go away simply by making clean needles universally available and taking away the fear of arrest. Now, the first person to figure that out and do something about it on a national scale was that well-known, bleeding heart liberal Margaret Thatcher. And she put in the world's first national needle exchange program and other countries followed suit, Australia, The Netherlands and few others, and in all of those countries, you can see, not more than four percent ever became infected with HIV, of injectors.In places that didn't do this, New York City for example, Moscow, Jakarta, we're talking, at its peak, one in two injectors infected with this fatal disease. Now, Margaret Thatcher didn't do this because she has any great love for junkies. She did it because she ran a country that had a national health service. So, if she didn't invest in effective prevention, she was going to have pick up the costs of treatment later on, and obviously those are much higher. So she was making a politically rational decision. Now, if I take out my public health nerd glasses here, and look at these data, it seems like a no-brainer, doesn't it. But in this country, where the government apparently does not feel compelled to provide health care for citizens, we've taken a very different approach. So what we've been doing in the United States is reviewing the data, endlessly reviewing the data. So these are reviews of hundreds of studies by all the big muckety-mucks of the scientific pantheon in the United States, and these are the studies that show needle programs are effective, quite a lot of them. Now, the ones that show that needle programs aren't effective -- you think that's one of these annoying dynamic slides, and I'm going to press my dongle and the rest of it's going to come up, but no, that's the whole slide.(Laughter)There is nothing on the other side. So, completely irrational, you would think, except that, wait a minute, politicians are rational too, and they're responding to what they think the votes want. So what we see is that voters respond very well to things like this and not quite so well to things like this.(Laughter)So it becomes quite rational to deny services to injectors. Now let's talk about sex. Are we any more rational about sex? Well, I'm not even going to address the clearly irrational positions of people like the Catholic Church, who think somehow that if you give out condoms, everyone's going to run out and have sex. I don't know if Pope Benedict watches TEDTalks online, but if you do, I've got news for you Benedict. I carry condoms all the time, and I never get laid. (Laughter) It's not that easy. Here, maybe you'll have better luck.(Applause)Okay, seriously, HIV is actually not that easy to transmit sexually. So, it depends on how much virus there is in your blood and in your body fluids. And what we've got is a very, very high level of virus, right at the beginning, when you're first infected, then you start making antibodies, and then it bumps along at quite low levels for a long time, 10 or 12 years, you have spikes if you get another sexually transmitted infection, but basically, nothing much is going on until you start to get symptomatic AIDS. And by that stage, over here, you're not looking great, you're not feeling great, you're not having that much sex.So the sexual transmission of HIV is essentially determined by how many partners you have in these very short spaces of time when you have peak viremia. Now, this makes people crazy because it means that you have to talk about some groups having more sexual partners in shorter spaces of time than other groups, and that's considered stigmatizing. I've always been a bit curious about that because I think stigma is a bad thing, whereas lots of sex is quite a good thing, but we'll leave that be. The truth is that 20 years of very good research have shown us that there are groups that are more likely to turn over large numbers of partners in a short space of time, and those groups are, globally, people who sell sex and their more regular partners, they are gay men on the party scene who have, on average, three times more partners than straight people on the party scene, and they are heterosexuals who come from countries that have traditions of polygamy and relatively high levels of female autonomy, and almost all of those countries are in east or southern Africa. And that is reflected in the epidemic that we have today.So you can see these horrifying figures from Africa. These are all countries in southern Africa where between one in seven and one in three of all adults are infected with HIV. Now, in the rest of the world, we've got basically nothing going on in the general population, very, very low levels, but we have extraordinarily high levels of HIV in these other populations who are at highest risk, so drug injectors, sex workers, and gay men. And you'll note that's the local data from Los Angeles. 25 percent prevalence among gay men. Of course, you can't get HIV just by having unprotected sex. You can only HIV by having unprotected sex with a positive person.In most of the world, these few prevention failures not withstanding, we are actually doing quite well these days in commercial sex. Condom use rates are between 80 and 100 percent in commercial sex in most countries. And, again, it's because of an alignment of the incentives. What's rational for public health is also rational for individual sex workers because it's really bad for business to have another STI. No one wants it. And, actually, clients don't want to go home with a drip either. So, essentially, you're able to achieve quite high rates of condom use in commercial sex.But in "intimate" relations, it's much more difficult because, with your wife or your boyfriend, or someone that you hope might turn into one of those things, we have this illusion of romance and trust and intimacy, and nothing is quite so unromantic as the, "my condom or yours, darling?" question. So, in the face of that, you really need quite a strong incentive to use condoms.This, for example. This gentleman's called Joseph. He's from Haiti, and he has AIDS, and he's probably not having a lot of sex right now, but he is a reminder in the population, of why you might want to be using condoms. This is also in Haiti and is a reminder of why you might want to be having sex, perhaps. Now, funnily enough, this is also Joseph after six months on antiretroviral treatment. Not for nothing do we call it the Lazarus Effect. But it is changing the equation of what's rational in sexual decision making. So, what we've got -- some people say, "Oh, it doesn't matter very much because, actually, treatment is effective prevention because it lowers your viral load and therefore makes it more difficult to transmit HIV." So, if you look at the viremia thing again, if you do start treatment when you're sick, well, what happens? Your viral load comes down. But compared to what? What happens if you're not on treatment? Well, you die, so your viral load goes to zero. And all of this green stuff here, including the spikes, which are because you couldn't get to the pharmacy or you ran out of drugs, or you went on a three day party binge and forgot to take your drugs, or because you've started to get resistance, or whatever, all of that is virus that wouldn't be out there, except for treatment.Now, am I saying, oh, well, great prevention strategy, let's just stop treating people? Of course not. Of course not, we need to expand antiretroviral treatment as much as we can. But what I am doing is calling into question those people who say that more treatment is all the prevention we need. That's simply not necessarily true, and I think we can learn a lot from the experience of gay men in rich countries where treatment has been widely available for going on 15 years now, and what we've seen is that, actually, condom use rates, which were very, very high -- the gay community responded very rapidly to HIV, with extremely little help from public health nerds, I would say -- that condom use rate has come down dramatically since treatment for two reasons really. One is the assumption of, "Oh well, if he's infected, he's probably on meds, and his viral load's going to be low, so I'm pretty safe."And the other thing is that people are simply not as scared of HIV as they were of AIDS, and rightly so. AIDS was a disfiguring disease that killed you, and HIV is an invisible virus that makes you take a pill every day. And that's boring, but is it as boring as having to use a condom every time you have sex, no matter how drunk you are, no matter how many poppers you've taken, whatever? If we look at the data, we can see that the answer to that question is mhmm.So these are data from Scotland. You see the peak in drug injectors before they started the national needle exchange program. Then it came way down and both in heterosexuals, mostly in commercial sex and in drug users, you've really got nothing much going on after treatment begins, and that's because of that alignment of incentives that I talked about earlier. But in gay men, you've got quite a dramatic rise starting three or four years after treatment became widely available. This is of new infections.What does that mean? It means that the combined effect of being less worried and having more virus out there in the population, more people living longer, healthier lives, more likely to be getting laid with HIV, is outweighing the effects of lower viral load, and that's a very worrisome thing. What does it mean? It means we need to be doing more prevention, the more treatment we have.Is that what's happening? No, and I call it the compassion conundrum. We've talked a lot about compassion the last couple of days. And what's happening really is that people are unable quite to bring themselves to put in good sexual and reproductive health services for sex workers, unable quite to be giving out needles to junkies, but once they've gone from being transgressive people, whose behaviors we don't want to condone, to being AIDS victims, we come over all compassionate and buy them incredibly expensive drugs for the rest of their lives. It doesn't make any sense from a public health point of view.I want to give, what's very nearly the last word, to Ines. Ines is a a transgender hooker on the streets of Jakarta. She's a chick with a dick. Why does she do that job? Well, of course, because she's forced into it because she doesn't have a better option, et cetera, et cetera, and if we could just teach her to sew and get her a nice job in a factory, all would be well. This is what factory workers earn in an hour in Indonesia, on average, 20 cents. It varies a bit province to province. I do speak to sex workers, 15,000 of them for this particular slide. And this is what sex workers say they earn in an hour. So, it's not a great job, but for a lot of people it really is quite a rational choice. Okay, Ines.We've got the tools, the knowledge and the cash, and commitment to preventing HIV too.Ines: So why is prevalence still rising? It's all politics. When you get to politics, nothing makes sense.Elizabeth Pisani: "When you get to politics, nothing makes sense." So, from the point of view of a sex worker, politicians are making no sense. From the point of view of a public health nerd, junkies are doing dumb things. I mean the truth is that everyone has a different rationale. There are as many different ways of being rational as there are human beings on the planet, and that's one of the glories of human existence. But those ways of being rational are not independent of one another. So it's rational for a drug injector to share needles because of a stupid decision that's made by a politician, and it's rational for a politician to make that stupid decision because they're responding to what they think the voters want. But here's the thing: We are the voters. We're not all of them, of course, but TED is a community of opinion leaders, and everyone who's in this room, and everyone who's watching this out there on the web, I think has a duty to demand of their politicians that we make policy based on scientific evidence and on common sense. It's going to be really hard for us to individually affect what's rational for every Frankie and every Ines out there. But you can at least use your vote to stop politicians doing stupid things that spread HIV.Thank you.
			</doc>
				<q  q_id="1" >
					<q_str>Which academic discipline does Elizabeth Pisani study?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >biochemistry</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >economics</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >human geography</answer>
					<answer a_id='4'  correct="Yes">epidemiology</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >medicine</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="2" >
					<q_str>Where was Elizabeth Pisani's friend incarcerated?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >in the Philippines </answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >in the Taiwan Island</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >in the Islands of Malaysia</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >in the Greater Sunda Islands archipelago</answer>
					<answer a_id='5'  correct="Yes">in the Lesser Sunda Islands archipelago</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="3" >
					<q_str>In Frankie's jail, how was diamorphine taken?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >by smoking</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >by sniffing</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >by suppository</answer>
					<answer a_id='4'  correct="Yes">by intravenous injection</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >by mouth</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="4" >
					<q_str>Why is it dangerous to use a dirty needle?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >because you can be put in a jail</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >because you can get killed</answer>
					<answer a_id='3'  correct="Yes">because you can get infected by HIV</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >because the law does not allow it</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >because there are no clean needles</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="5" >
					<q_str>Why is it that a person caught carrying a needle in Indonesia can be put in jail?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1'  correct="Yes">as the consumption of drugs is prohibited</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >as it is forbidden to move around on foot</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >as the selling of needles is prohibited</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >as needles are considered a weapon</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >as needles may transmit AIDS</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="6" >
					<q_str>Why did a former UK Prime Minister start a needle exchange program?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >in order to sell more needles</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >in order to allow HIV to spread</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >in order to improve the health service</answer>
					<answer a_id='4'  correct="Yes">in order to prevent the spread of HIV</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >in order to reduce the sale of drugs</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="7" >
					<q_str>What does Elizabeth Pisani think about the Catholic Church's position on sex?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >she thinks it is completely rational</answer>
					<answer a_id='2'  correct="Yes">she thinks it is completely illogical</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >she thinks it is completely correct</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >she thinks it is completely normal</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >she thinks it is completely acceptable</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="8" >
					<q_str>How long does it take from the first contagion to the appearance of the symptoms of AIDS?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >2-4 years</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >4-6 years</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >6-8 years</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >8-10 years</answer>
					<answer a_id='5'  correct="Yes">10-12 years</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="9" >
					<q_str>Why is it that people who have frequent sexual intercourse with many different partners risk getting infected by HIV?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >as the level of antibodies is higher</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >as the level of antibodies is lower</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >as the AIDS symptoms have not yet started</answer>
					<answer a_id='4'  correct="Yes">as the probability of meeting a partner who has just been infected is higher</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >as the probability of meeting a partner who has not been infected is higher</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="10" >
					<q_str>Who wrote "People do stupid things. That's what spreads HIV"?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1'  correct="Yes">Elizabeth Pisani</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >Frankie</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >a friend of Elizabeth Pisani</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >the brother of Elizabeth Pisani</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >a drug addict</answer>
				</q>
		</reading-test>
		<reading-test r_id="4">
			<doc d_id="4">
Emily Oster flips our thinking on AIDS in AfricaSo I want to talk to you today about AIDS in sub-Saharan Africa. And this is a pretty well-educated audience, so I imagine you all know something about AIDS. You probably know that roughly 25 million people in Africa are infected with the virus, and that AIDS is a disease of poverty. And that if we can bring Africa out of poverty, we would decrease AIDS as well. If you know something more, you probably know that Uganda, to date, is the only country in sub-Saharan Africa that has had success in combating the epidemic, using a campaign that encouraged people to abstain, be faithful, and use condoms -- the ABC campaign. They decreased their prevalence in the 1990s from about 15 percent to 6 percent over just a few years. If you follow policy, you probably know that a few years ago the president pledged 15 billion dollars to fight the epidemic over five years, and a lot of that money is going to go to programs that try to replicate Uganda and use behavior change to encourage people and decrease the epidemic.So today I'm going to talk about some things that you might not know about the epidemic. And then, actually, I'm also going to challenge some of these things that you think that you do know. And to do that I'm going to talk about my research as an economist on the epidemic. And I'm not really going to talk much about the economy. I'm not going to tell you about exports and prices. But I'm going to use tools and ideas that are familiar to economists to think about a problem that's more traditionally part of public health and epidemiology. And I think in that sense, this fits really nicely with this lateral thinking idea. Here I'm really using the tools of one academic discipline to think about problems of another.So we think, first and foremost, AIDS is a policy issue. And probably for most people in this room, that's how you think about it. But this talk is going to be about understanding facts about the epidemic. It's going to be about thinking about how it evolves, and how people respond to it. I think it may seem like I'm ignoring the policy stuff, which is really the most important, but I'm hoping that at the end of this talk you will conclude that we actually cannot develop effective policy unless we really understand how the epidemic works.And the first thing that I want to talk about, the first thing I think we need to understand, is: How do people respond to the epidemic? So AIDS is a sexually transmitted infection, and it kills you. So this means that in a place with a lot of AIDS, there's a really significant cost of sex. If you're an uninfected man living in Botswana, where the HIV rate is 30 percent, if you have one more partner this year -- a long-term partner, girlfriend, mistress -- your chance of dying in 10 years increases by three percentage points.That is a huge effect. And so I think that we really feel like, then people should have less sex. And in fact among gay men in the US we did see that kind of change in the 1980s. So if we look in this particularly high-risk sample, and they're being asked, "Did you have more than one unprotected sexual partner in the last two months?" Over a period from '84 to '88, that share drops from about 85 percent to 55 percent. It's a huge change, in a very short period of time.We didn't see anything like that in Africa. So we don't have quite as good data, but you can see here the share of single men having pre-marital sex, or married men having extra-marital sex, and how that changes from the early '90s to late '90s, and late '90s to early 2000s. The epidemic is getting worse. People are learning more things about it ... we see almost no change in sexual behavior. These are just tiny decreases -- two percentage points -- not significant.This seems puzzling, but I'm going to argue you shouldn't be surprised by this. And that to understand this, you need to think about health the way than an economist does -- as an investment. So if you're a software engineer and you're trying to think about whether to add some new functionality to your program, it's important to think about how much it costs. It's also important to think about what the benefit is. And one part of that benefit is how much longer you think this program is going to be active. If version 10 is coming out next week, there's no point in adding more functionality into version nine.But your health decisions are the same. Every time you have a carrot instead of a cookie, every time you go to the gym instead of going to the movies, that's a costly investment in your health. But how much you want to invest is going to depend on how much longer you expect to live in the future -- even if you don't make those investments. AIDS is the same kind of thing. It's costly to avoid AIDS. People really like to have sex. But you know, it has a benefit in terms of future longevity. But life expectancy in Africa, even without AIDS, is really, really low: 40 or 50 years in a lot of places. I think it's possible, if we think about that intuition, and think about that fact, that maybe that explains some of this low behavior change.But we really need to test that. And a great way to test that is to look across areas in Africa and see: do people with more life expectancy change their sexual behavior more? And the way that I'm going to do that is, I'm going to look across areas with different levels of malaria. So malaria is a disease that kills you. It's a disease that kills a lot of adults in Africa, in addition to a lot of children. And so people who live in areas with a lot of malaria are going to have lower life expectancy than people who live in areas with limited malaria. So one way to test to see whether we can explain some of this behavior change by differences in life expectancy is to look and see is there more behavior change in areas where there's less malaria.So that's what this figure shows you. This shows you -- in areas with low malaria, medium malaria, high malaria -- what happens to the number of sexual partners as you increase HIV prevalence. If you look at the blue line, the areas with low levels of malaria, you can see in those areas, actually, the number of sexual partners is decreasing a lot as HIV prevalence goes up. Areas with medium levels of malaria decreases some -- it doesn't decrease as much. And areas with high levels of malaria -- actually, it's increasing a little bit, although that's not significant.This is not just through malaria. Young women who live in areas with high maternal mortality change their behavior less in response to HIV than young women who live in areas with low maternal mortality. There's another risk, and they respond less to this existing risk.So by itself, I think this tells a lot about how people behave. It tells us something about why we see limited behavior change in Africa.But it also tells us something about policy. Even if you only cared about AIDS in Africa, it might still be a good idea to invest in malaria, in combating poor indoor air quality, improving maternal mortality rates. Because if you improve those things, then people are going to have an incentive to avoid AIDS on their own. But it also tells us something about one of these facts that we talked about before. Education campaigns, like the one that the president is focusing on in his funding, may not be enough. At least not alone. If people have no incentive to avoid AIDS on their own -- even if they know everything about the disease -- they still may not change their behavior.So the other thing that I think we learn here is that AIDS is not going to fix itself. People aren't changing their behavior enough to decrease the growth in the epidemic. So we're going to need to think about policy and what kind of policies might be effective.And a great way to learn about policy is to look at what worked in the past. The reason that we know that the ABC campaign was effective in Uganda is we have good data on prevalence over time. In Uganda we see the prevalence went down. We know they had this campaign. That's how we learn about what works. It's not the only place we had any interventions. Other places have tried things, so why don't we look at those places and see what happened to their prevalence?Unfortunately, there's almost no good data on HIV prevalence in the general population in Africa until about 2003. So if I asked you, "Why don't you go and find me the prevalence in Burkina Faso in 1991?" You get on Google, you Google -- and you find, actually the only people tested in Burkina Faso in 1991 are STD patients and pregnant women. Which is not a terribly representative group of people. Then if you poked a little more, you looked a little more at what was going on, you'd find that actually that was a pretty good year. Because in some years the only people tested are IV drug users. But even worse -- some years it's only IV drug users, some years it's only pregnant women. We have no way to figure out what happened over time. We have no consistent testing.And in the last few years, we've actually done some good testing. In Kenya, in Zambia, and a bunch of countries, there's been testing in random samples of the population. But this leaves us with a big gap in our knowledge. So I can tell you what the prevalence was in Kenya in 2003, but I can't tell you anything about 1993 or 1983.So this is a problem for policy, It was a problem for my research. And I started thinking about how else might we figure out what the prevalence of HIV was in Africa in the past. And I think that the answer is, we can look at mortality data, and we can use mortality data to figure out what the prevalence was in the past.To do this, we're going to have to rely on the fact that AIDS is a very specific kind of disease. It kills people in the prime of their lives. Not a lot of other diseases have that profile. And you can see here: this is a graph of death rates by age in Botswana and Egypt. Botswana is a place with a lot of AIDS, Egypt is a place without a lot of AIDS. And you see they have pretty similar death rates among young kids and old people. That suggests it's pretty similar levels of development.But in this middle region, between 20 and 45, the death rates in Botswana are much, much, much higher than in Egypt. But since there are very few other diseases that kill people, we can really attribute that mortality to HIV. But because people who died this year of AIDS got it a few years ago, we can use this data on mortality to figure out what HIV prevalence was in the past. So it turns out, if you use this technique, actually your estimates of prevalence are very close to what we get from testing random samples in the population -- but they're very, very different than what UNAIDS tells us the prevalences are.So this is a graph of prevalence estimated by UNAIDS, and prevalence based on the mortality data for the years in the late 1990s in nine countries in Africa. You can see almost without exception, the UNAIDS estimates are much higher than the mortality-based estimates. UNAIDS tell us that the HIV rate in Zambia is 20 percent, and mortality estimates suggest it's only about 5 percent And these are not, you know, trivial differences in mortality rates. So this is another way to see this. You can see that for the prevalence to be as high as UNAIDS says, we have to really see 60 deaths per 10,000 rather than 20 deaths per 10,000 in this age group.I'm going to talk a little bit in a minute about actually how we can use this kind of information to learn something that's going to help us think about the world. But this also tells us that one of these facts that I mentioned in the beginning may not be quite right. If you think that 25 million people are infected, if you think that the UNAIDS numbers are much too high, maybe that's more like 10 or 15 million. It doesn't mean that AIDS isn't a problem. It's a gigantic problem. But it does suggest that that number might be a little big. What I really want to do, is I want to use this new data to try to figure out what makes the HIV epidemic grow faster or slower.And I said in the beginning, I wasn't going to tell you about exports. When I started working on these projects, I was not thinking at all about economics, but eventually it kind of sucks you back in. So I am going to talk about exports and prices. And I want to talk about the relationship between economic activity, in particular export volume, and HIV infections.So obviously, as an economist, I'm deeply familiar with the fact that development, that openness to trade is really good for developing countries. It's good for improving people's lives. But openness and inter-connectiveness, it comes with a cost when we think about disease. I don't think this should be a surprise. On Wednesday, I learned from Laurie Garrett that I'm definitely going to get the bird flu, and I wouldn't be at all worried about that if we never had any contact with Asia.And HIV is actually particularly closely linked to transit. The epidemic was introduced to the US by actually one male steward on an airline flight, who got the disease in Africa and brought it back. And that was the genesis of the entire epidemic in the US. In Africa, epidemiologists have noted for a long time that truck drivers and migrants are more likely to be infected than other people. That areas with a lot of economic activity -- with a lot of roads, with a lot of urbanization -- those areas have higher prevalence than others.But that actually doesn't mean at all that if we gave people more exports, more trade, that that would increase prevalence. By using this new data, using this information about prevalence over time, we can actually test that. And so it seems to be -- fortunately, I think -- it seems to be the case that these things are positively related. More exports means more AIDS. And that effect is really big. So the data that I have suggests that if you double export volume, it will lead to a quadrupling of new HIV infections.So this has important implications both for forecasting and for policy. From a forecasting perspective, if we know where trade is likely to change, for example, because of the African Growth and Opportunities Act, or other policies that encourage trade, we can actually think about which areas are likely to be heavily infected with HIV. And we can go and we can try to have pre-emptive preventive measures there. Likewise, as we're developing policies to try to encourage exports, if we know there's this externality -- this extra thing that's going to happen as we increase exports -- we can think about what the right kinds of policies are.But it also tells us something about one of these things that we think that we know. Even though it is the case that poverty is linked to AIDS, in the sense that Africa is poor and they have a lot of AIDS, it's not necessarily the case that improving poverty -- at least in the short run -- that improving exports and improving development, it's not necessarily the case that's going to lead to a decline in HIV prevalence.So throughout this talk I've mentioned a few times the special case of Uganda, and the fact that it's the only country in sub-Saharan Africa with successful prevention. It's been widely heralded. It's been replicated in Kenya, and Tanzania, and South Africa and many other places. But now I want to actually also question that. Because it is true that there was a decline in prevalence in Uganda in the 1990s. It's true that they had an education campaign. But there was actually something else that happened in Uganda in this period.There was a big decline in coffee prices. Coffee is Uganda's major export. Their exports went down a lot in the early 1990s -- and actually that decline lines up really, really closely with this decline in new HIV infections. So you can see that both of these series -- the black line is export value, the red line is new HIV infections -- you can see they're both increasing. Starting about 1987, they're both going down a lot. And then actually they track each other a little bit on the increase later in the decade.So if you combine the intuition and this figure with some of the data that I talked about before, it suggests that somewhere between 25 percent and 50 percent of the decline in prevalence in Uganda actually would have happened even without any education campaign.But that's enormously important for policy. We're spending so much money to try to replicate this campaign, And if it was only 50 percent as effective as we think that it was, then there's all sorts of other things maybe we should be spending our money on instead. Trying to change transmission rates by treating other sexually transmitted diseases. Trying to change them by engaging in male circumcision. There's tons of other things that we should think about doing. And maybe this tells us that we should be thinking more about those things.I hope that in the last 16 minutes I've told you something that you didn't know about AIDS, and I hope that I've gotten you questioning a little bit some of the things that you did know. And I hope that I've convinced you maybe that it's important to understand things about the epidemic, in order to think about policy.But more than anything, you know, I'm an academic. And when I leave here, I'm going to go back and sit in my tiny office, and my computer, and my data -- and the thing that's most exciting about that is every time I think about research, there are more questions. There's more things that I think that I want to do. And what's really, really great about being here is I'm sure that the questions that you guys have are very, very different than the questions that I think up myself. And I can't wait to hear about what they are. So thank you very much.
			</doc>
				<q  q_id="1" >
					<q_str>Why is AIDS called a disease of poverty?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1'  correct="Yes">as in areas with low income there are higher prevalence rates</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >as only poor people are affected by it</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >as it is a political issue</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >as Uganda is mostly affected by it</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >as babies are mostly affected by it</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="2" >
					<q_str>What is Emily Oster's field of study?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >epidemiology</answer>
					<answer a_id='2'  correct="Yes">economics</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >public heath</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >political sciences</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >immunology</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="3" >
					<q_str>How are people infected by HIV?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >through aerial transmission</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >through genetic transmission</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >through direct contact with infected people</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >through the faecal-oral route</answer>
					<answer a_id='5'  correct="Yes">through sexual intercourse</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="4" >
					<q_str>In which country is an HIV rate of 30% registered?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >in the world's second largest country </answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >in the largest European island</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >in the third largest country in Africa</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >in the country whose capital is Khartoum</answer>
					<answer a_id='5'  correct="Yes">in the former British protectorate of Bechuanaland</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="5" >
					<q_str>Even though people are aware of AIDS, why is there only a limited change in behaviour in Africa?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >as life expectancy in Africa is very high</answer>
					<answer a_id='2'  correct="Yes">as life expectancy in Africa is very low</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >as condoms are not widely distributed</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >as information is not comprehensible by everyone</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >as people are reluctant</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="6" >
					<q_str>Why might investing in malaria reduce the spread of AIDS?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >as the number of mosquitos would decrease</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >as people can be infected with AIDS through mosquito bites</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >as malaria is an infectious disease which causes thousands of deaths</answer>
					<answer a_id='4'  correct="Yes">as by improving life conditions, people are more motivated to avoid AIDS</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >as malaria is widespread in tropical and subtropical regions, including much of Sub-Saharan Africa</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="7" >
					<q_str>What is the relation between the prevalence of AIDS and the economic activity of a country?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >no relationship</answer>
					<answer a_id='2'  correct="Yes">they are closely correlated</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >they are independent from each other</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >when one increases the other decreases</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >they diminish proportionally</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="8" >
					<q_str>Which worker classes are most at risk of catching HIV in Africa?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >doctors and nurses</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >civil engineers and builders</answer>
					<answer a_id='3'  correct="Yes">lorry drivers and migrants</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >businessmen and managers</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >teachers and professors</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="9" >
					<q_str>How is it possible to reduce the transmission of HIV?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >by the removal of the fetus</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >by the removal of the uterus</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >by the removal of the ovary</answer>
					<answer a_id='4'  correct="Yes">by the removal of some or all of the foreskin from the penis</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >by the removal of the breast</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="10" >
					<q_str>How did HIV enter North America?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1'  correct="Yes">through a flight attendant infected by HIV</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >through a sailor infected by HIV</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >through a businessman infected by HIV</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >through a drug pusher infected by HIV</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >through an African diplomat infected by HIV</answer>
				</q>
		</reading-test>
	</topic>
	<topic t_id="2" t_name="Climate Change">
		<reading-test r_id="5">
			<doc d_id="5">
Al Gore warns on latest climate trendsLast year I showed these two slides so that demonstrate that the arctic ice cap, which for most of the last three million years has been the size of the lower 48 states, has shrunk by 40 percent. But this understates the seriousness of this particular problem because it doesn't show the thickness of the ice. The arctic ice cap is, in a sense, the beating heart of the global climate system. It expands in winter and contracts in summer. The next slide I show you will be a rapid fast forward of what's happened over the last 25 years. The permanent ice is marked in red. As you see, it expands to the dark blue. That's the annual ice in winter. And it contracts in summer. The so-called permanent ice, five years old or older, you can see is almost like blood, spilling out of the body here. In 25 years it's gone from this, to this.This is a problem because the warming heats up the frozen ground around the arctic ocean where there is a massive amount of frozen carbon which, when it thaws, is turned into methane by microbes. Compared to the total amount of global warming pollution in the atmosphere, that amount could double if we cross this tipping point. Already in some shallow lakes in Alaska methane is actively bubbling up out of the water. Professor Katey Walter from the University of Alaska went out with another team to another shallow lake last winter. Video: Whoa! (Laughter) Al Gore: She's okay. The question is whether we will be.And one reason is, this enormous heat sink heats up Greenland from the north. This is an annual melting river. But the volumes are much larger than ever. This is the Kangerlussuaq River in southwest Greenland. If you want to know how sea level rises from land-base ice melting this is where it reaches the sea. These flows are increasing very rapidly. At the other end of the planet, Antarctica the largest mass of ice on the planet. Last month scientists reported the entire continent is now in negative ice balance. And west Antarctica cropped up on top some under-sea islands, is particularly rapid in its melting. That's equal to 20 feet of sea level, as is Greenland.In the Himalayas, the third largest mass of ice, at the top you see new lakes, which a few years ago were glaciers. 40 percent of all the people in the world get half of their drinking water from that melting flow. In the Andes, this glacier is the source of drinking water for this city. The flows have increased. But when they go away, so does much of the drinking water. In California there has been a 40 percent decline in the Sierra snowpack. This is hitting the reservoirs. And the predictions, as you've read, are serious.This drying around the world has lead to a dramatic increase in fires. And the disasters around the world have been increasing at an absolutely extraordinary and unprecedented rate. Four times as many in the last 30 years as in the previous 75. This is a completely unsustainable pattern. If you look at in the context of history you can see what this is doing.In the last five years we've added 70 million tons of CO2 every 24 hours -- 25 million tons every day to the oceans. Look carefully at the area of the eastern Pacific, from the Americas, extending westward, and on either side of the Indian subcontinent, where there is a radical depletion of oxygen in the oceans. The biggest single cause of global warming, along with deforestation, which is 20 percent of it, is the burning of fossil fuels. Oil is a problem, and coal is the most serious problem. The United States is one of the two largest emitters, along with China. And the proposal has been to build a lot more coal plants.But we're beginning to see a sea change. Here are the ones that have been cancelled in the last few years with some green alternatives proposed. (Applause) However there is a political battle in our country. And the coal industries and the oil industries spent a quarter of a billion dollars in the last calendar year promoting clean coal, which is an oxymoron. That image reminded me of something. (Laughter) Around Christmas, in my home in Tennessee, a billion gallons of coal sludge was spilled. You probably saw it on the news. This, all over the country, is the second largest waste stream in America. This happened around Christmas. One of the coal industry's ads around Christmas was this one.Video:  Frosty the coal man is a jolly, happy soul. He's abundant here in America, and he helps our economy grow. Frosty the coal man is getting cleaner everyday. He's affordable and adorable, and workers keep their pay.Al Gore: This is the source of much of the coal in West Virginia. The largest mountaintop miner is the head of Massey Coal.Video: Don Blankenship: Let me be clear about it. Al Gore, Nancy Pelosi, Harry Reid, they don't know what they're talking about.Al Gore: So the Alliance for Climate Protection has launched two campaigns. This is one of them, part of one of them.Video: Actor: At COALergy we view climate change as a very serious threat to our business. That's why we've made it our primary goal to spend a large sum of money on an advertising effort to help bring out and complicate the truth about coal. The fact is, coal isn't dirty. We think it's clean -- smells good, too. So don't worry about climate change. Leave that up to us. (Laughter)Video: Actor: Clean coal, you've heard a lot about it. So let's take a tour of this state-of-the-art clean coal facility. Amazing! The machinery is kind of loud. But that's the sound of clean coal technology. And while burning coal is one of the leading causes of global warming, the remarkable clean coal technology you see here changes everything. Take a good long look, this is today's clean coal technology.Al Gore: Finally the positive alternative meshes with our economic challenge and our national security challenge.Video: Narrator: America is in crisis, the economy, national security, the climate crisis. The thread that links them all, our addiction to carbon based fuels, like dirty coal and foreign oil. But now there is a bold new solution to get us out of this mess. Repower America with 100 percent clean electricity, within 10 years. A plan to put America back to work, make us more secure, and help stop global warming. Finally, a solution that's big enough to solve our problems. Repower America. Find out more.Al Gore: This is the last one.Video: Narrator: It's about repowering America. One of the fastest ways to cut our dependence on old dirty fuels that are killing our planet. Man: Future's over here. Wind, sun, a new energy grid. Man # 2: New investments to create high paying jobs. Narrator: Repower America. It's time to get real.Al Gore: There is an old African proverb that says, "If you want to go quickly, go alone. If you want to go far, go together." We need to go far, quickly. Thank you very much. (Applause)
			</doc>
				<q  q_id="1" >
					<q_str>What is the result if frozen carbon thaws?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1'  correct="Yes">methane</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >microbes</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >polution</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >ice</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >ocean</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="2" >
					<q_str>Where is the third largest mass of ice in the world?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >Greenland</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >Alaska</answer>
					<answer a_id='3'  correct="Yes">Asia</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >Africa</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >the Andes</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="3" >
					<q_str>What could be a consequence of a reduction in Arctic ice?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >higher sea level</answer>
					<answer a_id='2'  correct="Yes">more atmospheric pollution</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >less drinking water</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >more fires</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >less droughts</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="4" >
					<q_str>Why are there now more fires?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >use of fossil fuels</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >global warming</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >use of clean coal</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >more atmospheric pollution</answer>
					<answer a_id='5'  correct="Yes">less water</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="5" >
					<q_str>Name one of the main reasons for global warming.</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >US energy model</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >use of clean coal</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >less arctic ice</answer>
					<answer a_id='4'  correct="Yes">use of coal</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >reforestation</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="6" >
					<q_str>What Danish region is being affected by Arctic ice melting?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >Faroe Islands</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >Alaska</answer>
					<answer a_id='3'  correct="Yes">Greenland</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >California</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >United States</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="7" >
					<q_str>Why is methane present in Alaskan lakes?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >emission of carbon dioxide</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >melting of Antarctic soil</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >burning of fossil fuels</answer>
					<answer a_id='4'  correct="Yes">the reduction of arctic ice</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >reduction of glaciers</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="8" >
					<q_str>Which Asian country is one of the highest emitters of carbon dioxide?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >Japan</answer>
					<answer a_id='2'  correct="Yes">China</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >the Himalayas</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >India</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >US</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="9" >
					<q_str>In which American state has a high amount of snow been melting?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >Alaska</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >Tennessee</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >West Virginia</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >Arizona</answer>
					<answer a_id='5'  correct="Yes">California</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="10" >
					<q_str>What consequence would the use of renewable energies have in the US?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1'  correct="Yes">new job opportunities</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >a higher dependency on fossil fuels</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >a decrease in toxic dumps</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >a higher use of clean coal</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >less responsible use of energy</answer>
				</q>
		</reading-test>
		<reading-test r_id="6">
			<doc d_id="6">
Al Gore's new thinking on the climate crisisI have given the slide show that I gave here two years ago about 2,000 times. I'm giving a short slide show this morning that I'm giving for the very first time, so -- well it's -- I don't want or need to raise the bar; I'm actually trying to lower the bar. Because I've cobbled this together to try to meet the the challenge of this session.And I was reminded by Karen Armstrong's fantastic presentation that religion really properly understood is not about belief, but about behavior. Perhaps we should say the same thing about optimism. How dare we be optimistic? Optimism is sometimes characterized as a belief, an intellectual posture. As Mahatma Gandhi famously said, "You must become the change you wish to see in the world." And the outcome about which we wish to be optimistic is not going to be created by the belief alone, except to the extent that the belief brings about new behavior. But the word "behavior" is also, I think, sometimes misunderstood in this context. I'm a big advocate of changing the light bulbs and buying hybrids, and Tipper and I put 33 solar panels on our house, and dug the geothermal wells, and did all of that other stuff. But, as important as it is to change the light bulbs, it is more important to change the laws. And when we change our behavior in our daily lives, we sometimes leave out the citizenship part and the democracy part. In order to be optimistic about this, we have to become incredibly active as citizens in our democracy. In order to solve the climate crisis, we have to solve the democracy crisis. And we have one.I have been trying to tell this story for a long time. I was reminded of that recently by a woman who walked past the table I was sitting at, just staring at me as she walked past. She was in her '70s, looked like she had a kind face. I thought nothing of it until I saw from the corner of my eye she was walking from the opposite direction, also just staring at me. And so I said, "How do you do?" And she said, "You know, if you dyed your hair black, you would look just like Al Gore." (Laughter)Many years ago, when I was a young congressman, I spent an awful lot of time dealing with the challenge of nuclear arms control -- the nuclear arms race. And the military historians taught me during that quest that military conflicts are typically put into three categories: local battles, regional or theater wars, and the rare but all-important global, world war. Strategic conflicts. And each level of conflict requires a different allocation of resources a different approach, a different organizational model. Environmental challenges fall into the same three categories, and most of what we think about are local environmental problems: air pollution, water pollution, hazardous waste dumps. But there are also regional environmental problems, like acid rain from the Midwest to the Northeast, and from Western Europe to the Arctic, and from the Midwest out the Mississippi into the dead zone of the Gulf of Mexico. And there are lots of those. But the climate crisis is the rare but all-important global, or strategic, conflict. Everything is affected. And we have to organize our response appropriately. We need a worldwide, global mobilization for renewable energy, conservation, efficiency and a global transition to a low-carbon economy. We have work to do. And we can mobilize resources and political will. But the political will has to be mobilized in order to mobilize the resources.Let me show you these slides here. I thought I would start with the logo. What's missing here, of course, is the North Polar ice cap. Greenland remains. 28 years ago, this is what the polar ice cap -- the North Polar ice cap -- looked like at the end of the summer at the fall equinox. This last fall, I went to the Snow and Ice Data Center in Boulder, Colorado, and talked to the researchers here in Monterey at the Naval Postgraduate Laboratory. This is what's happened in the last 28 years. To put it in perspective, 2005 was the previous record. Here's what happened last fall that has really unnerved the researchers. The North Polar ice cap is the same size geographically. Doesn't look quite the same size, but it is exactly the same size as the United States, minus an area roughly equal to the state of Arizona. The amount that disappeared in 2005 was equivalent to everything east of the Mississippi. The extra amount that disappeared last fall was equivalent to this much. It comes back in the winter, but not as permanent ice: as thin ice. Vulnerable. The amount remaining could be completely gone in summer in as little as five years. That puts a lot of pressure on Greenland. Already, around the Arctic circle -- this is a famous village in Alaska. This is a town in Newfoundland. Antarctica. Latest studies from NASA. The amount of a moderate-to-severe snow melting of an area equivalent to the size of California."They were the best of times, they were the worst of times": the most famous opening sentence in English literature. I want to share briefly a "Tale of Two Planets." Earth and Venus are exactly the same size. Earth's diameter is about 400 kilometers larger, but essentially the same size. They have exactly the same amount of carbon. But the difference is, on Earth, most of the carbon has been leeched over time out of the atmosphere, deposited in the ground as coal, oil, natural gas, etc. On Venus, most of it is in the atmosphere. The difference is that our temperature is 59 degrees on average. On Venus, it's 855. This is relevant to our current strategy of taking as much carbon out of the ground as quickly as possible and putting it into the atmosphere. It's not because Venus is slightly closer to the Sun. It's three times hotter than Mercury, which is right next to the sun. Now, briefly, here's an image you've seen as one of the only old images, but I show it because I want to briefly give you CSI: Climate.The global scientific community says, man-made global warming pollution, put into the atmosphere, thickening this, is trapping more of the outgoing infrared. You all know that. At the last IPCC summary, the scientists wanted to say, "How certain are you?" They wanted to answer that "99 percent." The Chinese objected, and so the compromise was "more than 90 percent." Now, the skeptics say, "Oh, wait a minute, this could be variations in the -- in this energy coming in from the sun." If that were true, the stratosphere would be heated as well as the lower atmosphere, if it's more coming in. If it's more being trapped on the way out, then you would expect it to be warmer here and cooler here. Here is the lower atmosphere. Here's the stratosphere: cooler. CSI: Climate.Now, here's the good news. 68 percent of Americans now believe that human activity is responsible for global warming. 69 percent believe that the Earth is heating up in a significant way. There has been progress, but here is the key: when given a list of challenges to confront, global warming is still listed at near the bottom. What is missing is a sense of urgency. If you agree with the factual analysis, but you don't feel the sense of urgency, where does that leave you? Well, the Alliance for Climate Protection, which I head in conjunction with CurrentTV -- who did this pro-bono, did a worldwide contest to do commercials on how to communicate this. This is the winner.NBC -- I'll show all of the networks here -- the top journalists for NBC asked 956 questions in 2007 of the presidential candidates: two of them were about the climate crisis. ABC: 844 questions, two about the climate crisis. Fox: two. CNN: two. CBS: zero. From laughs to tears. This is one of the older tobacco commercials. So here's what we're doing. This is gasoline consumption in all of these countries. And us. But it's not just the developed nations. The developing countries are now following us and accelerating their pace. And actually, their cumulative emissions this year are the equivalent to where we were in 1965. And they're catching up very dramatically. The total concentrations: by 2025, they will be essentially where where we were in 1985. If the wealthy countries were completely missing from the picture, we would still have this crisis. But we have given to the developing countries the technologies and the ways of thinking that are creating the crisis. This is in Bolivia. Over -- over thirty years.This is peak fishing in a few seconds. The '60s. '70s. '80s. '90s. We have to stop this. And the good news is that we can. We have the technologies. We have to have a unified view of how to go about this: the struggle against poverty in the world and the challenge of cutting wealthy country emissions, all has a single, very simple solution.People say, "What's the solution?" Here it is. Put a price on carbon. We need a CO2 tax, revenue-neutral, to replace taxation on employment, which was invented by Bismark -- and some things have changed since the 19th century. In the poor world, we have to integrate the responses to poverty with the solutions to the climate crisis. Plans to fight poverty in Uganda are mooted if we do not solve the climate crisis.But responses can actually make a huge difference in the poor countries. This is a proposal that has been talked about a lot in Europe. This was from Nature Magazine. These are concentrating solar renewable-energy plants, linked in a so-called supergrid to supply all of the electrical power to Europe, largely from developing countries. High-voltage DC currents. This is not "pie in the sky;" this can be done.We need to do it for our own economy. The latest figures show that the old model is not working. There are a lot of great investments that you can make. If you are investing in tar sands or shale oil, then you have a portfolio that is crammed with sub-prime carbon assets. And it is based on an old model. Junkies find veins in their toes when the ones in their arms and their legs collapse. Developing tar sands and coal shale is the equivalent. Here are just a few of the investments that I personally think make sense. I have a stake in these, so I'll have a disclaimer there. But geothermal, concentrating solar, advanced photovaltaics, efficiency and conservation.You've seen this slide before, but there's a change. The only two countries that didn't ratify -- and now there's only one. Australia had an election. And there was a campaign in Australia that involved television and Internet and radio commercials to lift the sense of urgency for the people there. And we trained 250 people to give the slide show in every town and village and city in Australia. Lot of other things contributed to it, but the new Prime Minister announced that his very first priority would be to change Australia's position on Kyoto, and he has. Now, they came to an awareness partly because of the horrible drought that they had. This is Lake Lanier. My friend Heidi Cullins said that if we gave droughts names the way we give hurricanes names, we'd call the one in the southeast now Katrina, and we would say it's headed toward Atlanta. We can't wait for the kind of draught Australia had to change our political culture. Here's more good news. The cities supporting Kyoto in the U.S. are up to 780 -- and I thought I saw one go by there, just to localize this. Which is good news.Now to close, we heard a couple of days ago about the value of making individual heroism so commonplace that it becomes banal or routine. What we need is another hero generation. Those of us who are alive in the United States of America today especially, but also the rest of the world, have to somehow understand that history has presented us with a choice -- just as Jill Bolte Taylor was figuring out how to save her life while she was distracted by the amazing experience that she was going through. We now have a culture of distraction. But we have a planetary emergency. And we have to find a way to create, in the generation of those alive today, a sense of generational mission. I wish I could find the words to convey this. This was another hero generation that brought democracy to the planet. Another that ended slavery. And that gave women the right to vote. We can do this. Don't tell me that we don't have the capacity to do it. If we had just one week's worth of what we spend on the Iraq war, we could be well on the way to solving this challenge. We have the capacity to do it.One final point. I'm optimistic, because I believe we have the capacity, at moments of great challenge, to set aside the causes of distraction and rise to the challenge that history is presenting to us. Sometimes I hear people respond to the disturbing facts of the climate crisis by saying, "Oh, this is so terrible. What a burden we have." I would like to ask you to re-frame that. How many generations in all of human history have had the opportunity to rise to a challenge that is worthy of our best efforts? A challenge that can pull from us more than we knew we could do? I think we ought to approach this challenge with a sense of profound joy and gratitude that we are the generation about which, a thousand years from now, philharmonic orchestras and poets and singers will celebrate by saying, they were the ones that found it within themselves to solve this crisis and lay the basis for a bright and optimistic human future.Let's do that. Thank you very much.Chris Anderson: For so many people at TED, there is deep pain that basically a design issue -- at the end of the day, a design issue on a voting form -- one bad design issue meant that your voice wasn't being heard like that in the last eight years in a position where you could make these things come true. That hurts.Al Gore: You have no idea. (Laughter)CA: When you look at what the leading candidates in your own party are doing now -- I mean, there's -- are you excited by their plans on global warming?AG: The answer to the question is hard for me because, on the one hand, I think that we should feel really great about the fact that the Republican nominee -- certain nominee -- John McCain, and both of the finalists for the Democratic nomination -- all three have a very different and forward-leaning position on the climate crisis. All three have offered leadership, and all three are very different from the approach taken by the current administration. And I think that all three have also been responsible in putting forward plans and proposals. But the campaign dialogue that -- as illustrated by the questions -- that was put together by the League of Conservation Voters, by the way, the analysis of all the questions -- and, by the way, the debates have all been sponsored by something that goes by the Orwellian label, "Clean Coal." Has anybody noticed that? Every single debate has been sponsored by "Clean Coal." "Now, even lower emissions!"The richness and fullness of the dialogue in our democracy has not laid the basis for the kind of bold initiative that is really needed. So they're saying the right things and they may -- whichever of them is elected -- may do the right thing, but let me tell you: when I came back from Kyoto in 1997 with a feeling of great happiness that we'd gotten that breakthrough there, and then confronted the United States Senate, only one out of 100 senators was willing to vote to confirm, to ratify that treaty. Whatever the candidates say has to be laid alongside what the people say.This challenge is part of the fabric of our whole civilization. CO2 is the exhaling breath of our civilization, literally. And now we mechanized that process. Changing that pattern requires a scope, a scale, a speed of change that is beyond what we have done in the past. So that's why I began by saying, be optimistic in what you do, but be an active citizen Demand -- change the light bulbs, but change the laws. Change the global treaties. We have to speak up. We have to solve this democracy -- this -- We have sclerosis in our democracy. And we have to change that. Use the Internet. Go on the Internet. Connect with people. Become very active as citizens. Have a moratorium -- we shouldn't have any new coal fire generating plants that aren't able to capture and store CO2. Which means we have to quickly build these renewable sources. Now, nobody is talking on that scale. But I do believe that between now and November, it is possible. This Alliance for Climate Protection is going to launch a nationwide campaign -- grassroots mobilization, television ads, Internet ads, radio, newspaper -- with partnerships with everybody from the Girl Scouts to the hunters and fishermen.We need help. We need help.CA: In terms of your own personal role going forward, Al, is there something more than that you would like to be doing?AG: I have prayed that I would be able to find the answer to that question. What can I do? Buckminster Fuller once wrote, "If the future of all human civilization depended on me, what would I do? How would I be?" It does depend on all of us, but again, not just with the light bulbs. We, most of us here, are Americans. We have a democracy. We can change things, but we have to actively change. What's needed really is a higher level of consciousness. And that's hard to -- that's hard to create -- but it is coming. There's an old African proverb that some of you know that says, "If you want to go quickly, go alone; if you want to go far, go together." We have to go far quickly. So we have to have a change in consciousness. A change in commitment. A new sense of urgency. A new appreciation for the privilege that we have of undertaking this challenge.CA: Al Gore, thank you so much for coming to TED.AG: Thank you. Thank you very much.
			</doc>
				<q  q_id="1" >
					<q_str>In what country is the Snow and Ice Data Center located?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1'  correct="Yes">United States</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >Germany</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >Denmark</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >Mexico</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >Bolivia</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="2" >
					<q_str>What planet in the solar system has a size similar to our planet?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >Earth</answer>
					<answer a_id='2'  correct="Yes">Venus</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >Mercury</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >Saturn</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >Mars</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="3" >
					<q_str>What TV channel does the head of the Alliance for Climate Protection manage?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >CBS</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >Fox</answer>
					<answer a_id='3'  correct="Yes">CurrentTV</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >CNN</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >ESPN</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="4" >
					<q_str>How could the reduction of carbon dioxide emissions be promoted?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >encouraging the use of renewable energies</answer>
					<answer a_id='2'  correct="Yes">taxing CO2 emissions</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >reducing the use of fossil fuels</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >developing shale oil</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >increasing the number of hybrid cars</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="5" >
					<q_str>How can a  real change concerning climate change be brought about?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >using low-energy bulbs</answer>
					<answer a_id='2'  correct="Yes">changing current legislation</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >agreeing to the Kyoto protocol</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >using solar panels</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >encouraging the use of tar sands</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="6" >
					<q_str>Which relative of Al Gore has collaborated with him in making their house use renewable energy?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >his son</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >his father</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >his sister</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >his mother</answer>
					<answer a_id='5'  correct="Yes">his wife</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="7" >
					<q_str>Where has carbon from the Earth's atmosphere gone?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >it is still in the atmosphere</answer>
					<answer a_id='2'  correct="Yes">to form fossil fuels</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >to be part of the arctic ice cap</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >to pollute the air</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >to create acid rain</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="8" >
					<q_str>In what way are developing countries following the bad practices of rich countries?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >failing to find solutions to poverty</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >reducing the use of fossil fuels</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >increasing tobacco advertising</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >failing to apply legislation on pollution</answer>
					<answer a_id='5'  correct="Yes">increasing CO2 emissions</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="9" >
					<q_str>What action was taken in Australia in order to achieve a better understanding of the Kyoto protocol?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >broadcasting a discourse by Heidi Cullins about droughts</answer>
					<answer a_id='2'  correct="Yes">conducting a big campaign started by the Prime Minister</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >encouraging a better understanding of hurricanes</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >promoting the use of solar energy</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >changing legislation</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="10" >
					<q_str>What is the most important enviromental problem at a global level?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >acid rain</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >water pollution</answer>
					<answer a_id='3'  correct="Yes">climate change</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >nuclear weapons</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >CO2 emissions</answer>
				</q>
		</reading-test>
		<reading-test r_id="7">
			<doc d_id="7">
David Keith's unusual climate change ideaYou've all seen lots of articles on climate change, and here's yet another New York Times article, just like every other darn one you've seen. It says all the same stuff as all the other ones you've seen. It even has the same amount of headline as all the other ones you've seen. What's unusual about this one, maybe, is that it's from 1953. And the reason I'm saying this is that you may have the idea this problem is relatively recent. That people have just sort of figured out about it and now with Kyoto and the Governator and people beginning to actually do something, we may be on the road to a solution. The fact is: uh-uh. We've known about this problem for 50 years, depending on how you count it. We have talked about it endlessly over the last decade or so. And we've accomplished close to zip.This is the growth rate of CO2 in the atmosphere. You've seen this in various forms, but maybe you haven't seen this one. What this shows is that the rate of growth of our emissions is accelerating. And that it's accelerating even faster than what we thought was the worst case just a few years back. So that red line there was something that a lot of skeptics said the environmentalists only put in the projections to make the projections look as bad as possible. That emissions would never grow as fast as that red line. But in fact, they're growing faster.Here's some data from actually just 10 days ago, which shows this year's minimum of the Arctic Sea ice, and it's the lowest by far. And the rate at which the Arctic Sea ice is going away is a lot quicker than models. So despite all sorts of experts like me flying around the planet and burning jet fuel and politicians signing treaties, in fact you could argue the net effect of all this has been negative because it's just consumed a lot of jet fuel. (Laughter) No, no! In terms of what we really need to do to put the brakes on this very high inertial thing -- our big economy -- we've really hardly started. Really, we're doing this, basically. Really, not very much.I don't want to depress you too much. The problem is absolutely soluble, and even soluble in a way that's reasonably cheap. Cheap meaning sort of the cost of the military, not the cost of medical care. Cheap meaning a few percent of GDP. No, this is really important to have this sense of scale. So the problem is soluble, and the way we should go about solving it is, say, dealing with electricity production, which causes something like 43-or-so percent and rising of CO2 emissions. And we could do that by perfectly sensible things like conservation, and wind power, nuclear power and coal to CO2 capture, which are all things that are ready for giant scale deployment and work. All we lack is the action to actually spend the money to put those into place. Instead we spend our time talking.But nevertheless, that's not what I'm going to talk to you about tonight. What I'm going to talk to you about tonight is stuff we might do if we did nothing. And it's this stuff in the middle here which is what you do if you don't stop the emissions quickly enough. And you need to deal -- somehow break the link between human actions that change climate, and the climate change itself. And that's particularly important because of course, while we can adapt to climate change -- and it's important to be honest here -- there will be some benefits to climate change. Oh yes, I think it's bad. I've spent my whole life working to stop it. But one of the reasons it's politically hard is there are winners and losers -- not all losers. But of course, the natural world, polar bears. I spent time skiing across the sea ice for weeks at a time in the high Arctic. They will completely lose. And there's no adaption.So this problem is absolutely soluble. This geo-engineering idea, in it's simplest form, is basically the following: You could put signed particles, say sulfuric acid particles -- sulfates -- into the upper atmosphere, the stratosphere, where they'd reflect away sunlight and cool the planet. And I know for certain that that will work. Not that there aren't side effects, but I know for certain it will work. And the reason is: it's been done. And it was done not by us, not by me, but by nature.Here's Mount Pinatubo in the early '90s, that put a whole bunch of sulfur in the stratosphere with a sort of atomic bomb-like cloud. The result of that was pretty dramatic. After that, and some previous volcanoes we have, you see a quite dramatic cooling of the atmosphere. So this lower bar is the upper atmosphere, the stratosphere, and it heats up after these volcanoes. But you'll notice that in the upper bar, which is the lower atmosphere and the surface, it cools down because we shielded the atmosphere a little bit. There's no big mystery about it. There's lots of mystery in the details, and there's some bad side effects, like it partially destroys the ozone layer -- and I'll get to that in a minute. But it clearly cools down. And one other thing: it's fast. It's really important to say. So much of the other things that we ought to do, like slowing emissions, are intrinsically slow because it takes time to build all the hardware we need to reduce emissions. And not only that, when you cut emissions, you don't cut concentrations. Because concentrations, the amount of CO2 in the air, is the sum of emissions over time. So you can't step on the brakes very quickly. But if you do this, it's quick. And there are times you might like to do something quick.Another thing you might wonder about is does it work? Can you shade some sunlight and effectively compensate for the added CO2, and produce a climate sort of back to what it was originally? And the answer seems to be yes. So here are the graphs you've seen lots of times before. That's what the world looks like under one particular climate model's view with twice the amount of CO2 in the air. The lower graph is with twice the amount of CO2 and 1.8 percent less sunlight, and you're back to the original climate. And this graph from Ken Caldera. It's important to say came because Ken at a meeting that I believe Marty Hoffart was also at in the mid-'90s -- Ken and I stood up at the back of the meeting and said, "Geo-engineering won't work." And to the person who was promoting it said, "The atmosphere's much more complicated." Gave a bunch of physical reasons why it wouldn't do a very good compensation. Ken went and ran his models, and found that it did.This topic is also old. That report that landed on President Johnson's desk when I was two years old. 1965. That report, in fact, which had all the modern climate science -- the only thing they talked about doing was geo-engineering. It didn't even talk about cutting emissions, which is an incredible shift in our thinking about this problem. I'm not saying we shouldn't cut emissions. We should, but it made exactly this point. So in a sense, there's not much new. The one new thing is this essay. So I should say, I guess, that since the time of that original President Johnson report, and the various reports of the U.S. National Academy -- 1977, 1982, 1990 -- people always talked about this idea. Not as something that was foolproof, but as an idea to think about.But when climate became, politically, a hot topic -- if I may make the pun -- in the last 15 years, this became so un-PC we couldn't talk about it. It just sunk below the surface. We weren't allowed to speak about it. But in the last year, Paul Crutzen published this essay saying roughly what's all been said before: that maybe given our very slow rate of progress in solving this problem, and the uncertain impacts, we should think about things like this. He said roughly what's been said before. The big deal was he happened to have won the Nobel Prize for ozone chemistry. And so people took him seriously when he said we should think about this, even though there would be some ozone impacts. And in fact, he had some ideas to make them go away.There was all sorts of press coverage, all over the world, going right down to "Dr. Strangelove Saves the Earth," from the Economist. And that got me thinking -- I've worked on this topic on and off, but not so much technically -- and I was actually lying in bed thinking one night. And I thought about this child's toy -- hence, the title of my talk -- and I wondered if you could use the same physics that makes that thing spin 'round in the child's radiometer to levitate particles into the upper atmosphere and make them stay there. One of the problems with sulfates is they fall out quickly. The other problem is they're right in the ozone layer, and I'd prefer them above the ozone layer. And it turns out, I woke up the next morning, and I started to calculate this. It was very hard to calculate from first principles. I was stumped. But then I found out that there were all sorts of papers already published that addressed this topic because it happens already in the natural atmosphere. So it seems there are already fine particles that are levitated up to what we call the mesosphere, about 100 kilometers up -- that already have this effect.I'll tell you very quickly how the effect works. There are a lot of fun complexities that I'd love to spend the whole evening on, but I won't. But let's say you have sunlight hitting some particle and it's unevenly heated. So the side facing the sun is warmer, the side away cooler. Gas molecules that bounce off the warm side bounce away with some extra velocity because it's warm. And so you see a net force away from the sun. That's called the photophoretic force. There are a bunch of other versions of it that I and some collaborators have thought about how to exploit. And of course, we may be wrong -- this hasn't all been peer reviewed, we're in the middle of thinking about it -- but so far it seems good. But it looks like we could achieve long atmospheric lifetimes -- much longer than before -- because they're levitated. We can move things out of the stratosphere into the mesosphere, in principle solving the ozone problem. I'm sure there will be other problems that arise. Finally, we could make the particles migrate to over the poles, so we could arrange the climate engineering so it really focused on the poles. Which would have minimal bad impacts in the middle of the planet where we live and do the maximum job of what we might need to do -- which is cooling the poles in case of planetary emergency, if you like.This is a new idea that's crept up that may be, essentially, a cleverer idea than putting sulfates in. Whether this idea is right or some other idea is right, I think it's almost certain we will eventually think of cleverer things than just putting sulfur in. That if engineers and scientists really turned their minds to this, it's amazing how we can affect the planet. The one thing about this is that it gives us extraordinary leverage. This improved science and engineering will, whether we like it or not, give us more and more leverage to affect the planet. To control the planet. To give us weather and climate control -- not because we plan it, not because we want it, just because science delivers it to us bit by bit, with better knowledge of the way the system works and better engineering tools to effect it.Now suppose that space aliens arrived -- maybe they're going to land at the UN headquarters down the road here, or maybe they'll pick a smarter spot -- but suppose they arrive and they give you a box. And the box has two knobs. One knob is the knob for controlling global temperature. Maybe another knob is a knob for controlling CO2 concentrations. You might imagine that we would fight wars over that box. Because we have no way to agree about where to set the knobs. We have no global governance. And different people will have different places they want it set. Now I don't think that's going to happen. It's not very likely.But we're building that box. The scientists and the engineers of the world are building it piece by piece, in their labs. Even when they're doing it for other reasons. Even when they're thinking they're just working on protecting the environment. They have no interest in crazy ideas like engineering the whole planet. They develop science that makes it easier and easier to do. And so I guess my view on this is not that I want to do it -- I do not -- but that we should move this out of the shadows and talk about it seriously. Because sooner or later we'll be confronted with decisions about this, and it's better if we think hard about it, even if we want to think hard about reasons why we should never do it.I'll give you two different ways to think about this problem that are the beginning of my thinking about how to think about it. But what we need is not just a few oddballs like me thinking about this -- we need a broader debate. A debate that involves musicians, scientists, philosophers, writers, who get engaged with this question about climate engineering and think seriously about what its implications are. So here's one way to think about it, which is that we just do this instead of cutting emissions because it's cheaper. I guess the thing I haven't said about this is, it is absurdly cheap. It's conceivable that, say, using the sulfates method or this method I've come up with, you could create an ice age at a cost of .0001 percent of GDP. It's very cheap. We have a lot of leverage. It's not a good idea, but it's just important. I'll tell you how big the lever is -- the lever is that big. And that calculation isn't much in dispute. You might argue about the sanity of it, but the leverage is real. (Laughter)So because of this, we could deal with the problem simply by stopping reducing emissions, and just as the concentrations go up, we can increase the amount of geo-engineering. I don't think anybody takes that seriously. Because under this scenario, we walk further and further away from the current climate. We have all sorts of other problems like ocean acidification that come from CO2 in the atmosphere anyway. Nobody but maybe one or two very odd folks really suggest this.But here's a case which is harder to reject. Let's say that we don't do geo-engineering, we do what we ought to do, which is get serious about cutting emissions. But we don't really know how quickly we have to cut them. There's a lot of uncertainty about exactly how much climate change is too much. So let's say that we work hard, and we actually don't just tap the brakes, but we step hard on the brakes and really reduce emissions and eventually reduce concentrations. And maybe some day -- like 2075, October 23rd -- we finally reach that glorious day where concentrations have peaked and are rolling down the other side. And we have global celebrations, and we've actually started to -- you know -- we've seen the worst of it. But maybe on that day we also find that the Greenland ice sheet is really melting unacceptably fast, fast enough to put meters of sea level on the oceans in the next 100 years, and remove some of the biggest cities from the map. That's an absolutely possible scenario. We might decide at that point that even though geo-engineering was uncertain and morally unhappy, that it's a lot better than not geo-engineering. And that's a very different way to look at the problem. It's using this as risk control, not instead of action. It's saying that you do some geo-engineering for a little while to take the worst of the heat off, not that you'd use it as a substitute for action.But there is a problem with that view. And the problem is the following: knowledge that geo-engineering is possible makes the climate impacts look less fearsome. And that makes a weaker commitment to cutting emissions today. This is what economists call a moral hazard. And that's one of the fundamental reasons that this problem is so hard to talk about, and in general I think it's the underlying reason that it's been politically unacceptable to talk about this. But you don't make good policy by hiding things in a drawer.I'll leave you with three questions, and then one final quote. Should we do serious research on this topic? Should we have a national research program that looks at this? Not just at how you would do it better, but also what all the risks and downsides of it are. Right now you have a few enthusiasts talking about it, some in a positive side, some in a negative side -- but that's a dangerous state to be in because there's very little depth of knowledge on this topic. A very small amount of money would get us some. Many of us -- maybe now me -- think we should do that. But I have a lot of reservations. My reservations are principally about the moral hazard problem, and I don't really know how we can best avoid the moral hazard. I think there is a serious problem as you talk about this. People begin to think they don't need to work so hard to cut emissions.Another thing is: maybe we need a treaty. A treaty that decides who gets to do this. Right now we may think of a big rich country like the U.S. doing this. But it might well be that, in fact, if China wakes up in 2030 and realizes that the climate impacts are just unacceptable, they may not be very interested in our moral conversations about how to do this, and they may just decide they'd really rather have a geo-engineered world than a non-geoengineered world. And we'll have no international mechanism to figure out who makes the decision.So here's one last thought, which was said much, much better 25 years ago in the U.S. National Academy report than I can say today. And I think it really summarizes where we are here. That the CO2 problem, the climate problem that we've heard about, is driving lots of things, innovations in energy technologies, that will reduce emissions. But also, I think inevitably, it will drive us towards thinking about climate and weather control whether we like it or not. And it's time to begin thinking about it, even if the reason we're thinking about it is to construct arguments for why we shouldn't do it. Thank you very much.
			</doc>
				<q  q_id="1" >
					<q_str>When was a newspaper article published on climate change?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >at the beginning of 2000</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >in the 90s</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >in 1965</answer>
					<answer a_id='4'  correct="Yes">in the 1950s</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >in 2075</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="2" >
					<q_str>What kind of energy would help to reduce CO2 emissions?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1'  correct="Yes">nuclear</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >geothermal</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >hydraulic</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >electric</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >kinetic</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="3" >
					<q_str>What solution not tested by humans could contribute to reducing the climate change problem?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >the use of renewable energies</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >the reduction of CO2 emissions</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >investment in climate change by the governments of developed countries</answer>
					<answer a_id='4'  correct="Yes">the introduction of signed particles into the stratosphere</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >the protection of the environment</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="4" >
					<q_str>Why is it not enough to reduce CO2 emissions in order to fight against global warming?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >because there will be no efficient method for obtaining energy</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >because volcanic eruptions will keep emitting CO2 into the atmosphere</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >because the climate will already have changed irremediably</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >because it is impossible to reduce CO2 emissions</answer>
					<answer a_id='5'  correct="Yes">because the air will still contain high amounts of carbon dioxide</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="5" >
					<q_str>What effect related to climate change would the shading of sunlight have?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >the Earth would be darker</answer>
					<answer a_id='2'  correct="Yes">the Earth would be cooler</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >the concentration of CO2 would be lower</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >the sea level would be higher</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >solar energy would be impossible to use</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="6" >
					<q_str>What Nobel prize winner favours the use of geo-engineering in order to solve global warming?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1'  correct="Yes">Paul Crutzen</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >Al Gore</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >Marty Hoffart</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >Dr. Strangelove</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >Rajendra Pachauri</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="7" >
					<q_str>What is the advantage of using geo-engineering?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >it allows better control over electricity production</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >it can reduce the effect of volcanic eruptions</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >it can decrease CO2 concentrations</answer>
					<answer a_id='4'  correct="Yes">it can control the planet's temperature</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >it has been tested empirically</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="8" >
					<q_str>Besides global warming, what other consequence does the accumulation of CO2 have?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1'  correct="Yes">more acid in the ocean</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >less energy available</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >higher temperatures</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >more volcanic eruptions</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >more control over the climate</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="9" >
					<q_str>What atmospheric layer increases its temperature after volcanic eruptions?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >mesosphere</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >troposphere</answer>
					<answer a_id='3'  correct="Yes">stratosphere</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >thermosphere</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >exosphere</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="10" >
					<q_str>What could happen if the amount of atmospheric CO2 is not reduced?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >an energy crisis</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >the cooling of the planet</answer>
					<answer a_id='3'  correct="Yes">the flooding of some cities</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >less dependency on fossil fuels</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >an increase in the Arctic ice level</answer>
				</q>
		</reading-test>
		<reading-test r_id="8">
			<doc d_id="8">
Lee Hotz Inside an Antarctic time machineCome with me to the bottom of the world, Antarctica, the highest, driest, windiest, and yes, coldest region on Earth -- more arid than the Sahara and, in parts, colder than Mars. The ice of Antarctica glows with a light so dazzling, it blinds the unprotected eye. Early explorers rubbed cocaine in their eyes to kill the pain of it. The weight of the ice is such that the entire continent sags below sea level, beneath its weight. Yet, the ice of Antarctica is a calendar of climate change. It records the annual rise and fall of greenhouse gases and temperatures going back before the onset of the last ice ages. Nowhere on Earth offers us such a perfect record. And here, scientists are drilling into the past of our planet to find clues to the future of climate change.This past January, I traveled to a place called WAIS Divide, about 600 miles from the South Pole. It is the best place on the planet, many say, to study the history of climate change. There, about 45 scientists from the University of Wisconsin, the Desert Research Institute in Nevada and others have been working to answer an essential question about global warming. What is the exact relationship between levels of greenhouse gases and planetary temperatures? It's urgent work. We know that temperatures are rising. This past May was the warmest worldwide on record. And we know that levels of greenhouse gases are rising too. What we don't know is the exact, precise, immediate impact of these changes on natural climate patterns -- winds, ocean currents, precipitation rates, cloud formation, things that bear on the health and well-being of billions of people.Their entire camp, every item of gear, was ferried 885 miles from McMurdo Station, the main U.S. supply base on the coast of Antarctica. WAIS Divide itself though, is a circle of tents in the snow. In blizzard winds, the crew sling ropes between the tents so that people can feel their way safely to the nearest ice house and to the nearest outhouse. It snows so heavily there, the installation was almost immediately buried. Indeed, the researchers picked this site because ice and snow accumulates here 10 times faster than anywhere else in Antarctica. They have to dig themselves out every day. It makes for an exotic and chilly commute.(Laughter)But under the surface, is a hive of industrial activity centered around an eight-million-dollar drill assembly. Periodically, this drill, like a biopsy needle, plunges thousands of feet deep into the ice to extract a marrow of gases and isotopes for analysis. 10 times a day, they extract the 10-foot long cylinder of compressed ice crystals that contain the unsullied air and trace chemicals laid down by snow, season after season for thousands of years. It's really a time machine. At the peak of activity earlier this year, the researchers lowered the drill an extra hundred feet deeper into the ice every day and another 365 years deeper into the past. Periodically, they remove a cylinder of ice, like gamekeepers popping a spent shotgun shell from the barrel of a drill. They inspect it, they check it for cracks, for drill damage, for spalls, for chips.More importantly, they prepare it for inspection and analysis by 27 independent laboratories in the United States and Europe, who will examine it for 40 different trace chemicals related to climate, some in parts per quadrillion. Yes, I said that with a Q, quadrillion. They cut the cylinders up into three-foot sections for easier handling and shipment back to these labs, some 8,000 miles from the drill site. Each cylinder is a parfait of time.This ice formed as snow 15,800 years ago, when our ancestors were daubing themselves with paint and considering the radical new technology of the alphabet. Bathed in polarized light and cut in cross-section, this ancient ice reveals itself as a mosaic of colors, each one showing how conditions at depth in the ice have affected this material at depths where pressures can reach a ton per square inch. Every year, it begins with a snowflake, and by digging into fresh snow, we can see how this process is ongoing today. This wall of undisturbed snow, back-lit by sunlight, shows the striations of winter and summer snow, layer upon layer. Each storm scours the atmosphere, washing out dust, soot, trace chemicals, and depositing them on the snow pack year after year, millennia after millennia, creating a kind of periodic table of elements that at this point is more than 11,000 ft. thick. From this, we can detect an extraordinary number of things. We can see the calcium from the world's deserts, soot from distant wildfires, methane as an indicator of a Pacific monsoon, all wafted on winds from warmer latitudes to this remote and very cold place.Most importantly, these cylinders and this snow trap air. Each cylinder is about 10 percent ancient air, a pristine time capsule of greenhouse gases -- carbon dioxide, methane, nitrous oxide -- all unchanged from the day that snow formed and first fell. And this is the object of their scrutiny. But don't we already know what we need to know about greenhouse gases? Why do we need to study this anymore? Don't we already know how they affect temperatures? Don't we already know the consequenses of a changing climate on our settled civilization? The truth is, we only know the outlines, and what we don't completely understand, we can't properly fix. Indeed, we run the risk of making things worse.Consider, the single most successful international environmental effort of the 20th century, the Montreal Protocol, in which the nations of Earth banded together to protect the planet from the harmful effects of ozone-destroying chemicals used at that time in air conditioners, refrigerators and other cooling devices. We banned those chemicals, and we replaced them, unknowingly, with other substances that, molecule per molecule, are a hundred times more potent as heat-trapping, greenhouse gases than carbon dioxide.This process requires extraordinary precautions. The scientists must insure that the ice is not contaminated. Moreover, in this 8,000-mile journey, they have to insure this ice doesn't melt. Imagine juggling a snowball across the tropics. They have to, in fact, make sure this ice never gets warmer than about 20 degrees below zero, otherwise, the key gases inside it will dissipate. So, in the coldest place on Earth, they work inside a refrigerator. As they handle the ice, in fact, they keep an extra pair of gloves warming in an oven, so that, when their work gloves freeze and their fingers stiffen, they can don a fresh pair. They work against the clock and against the thermometer.So far, they've packed up about 4,500 ft. of ice cores for shipment back to the United States. This past season, They manhandled them across the ice to waiting aircraft. The 109th Air National Guard flew the most recent shipment of ice back to the coast of Antarctica, where it was boarded onto a freighter, shipped across the tropics to California, unloaded, put on a truck, driven across the desert to the National Ice Core Laboratory in Denver, Colorado, where, as we speak, scientists are now slicing this material up for samples, for analysis, to be distributed to the laboratories around the country and in Europe.Antarctica was this planet's last empty quarter -- the blind spot in our expanding vision of the world. Early explorers sailed off the edge of the map, and they found a place where the normal rules of time and temperature seem suspended. Here, the ice seems a living presence. the wind that rubs against it gives it voice. It is a voice of experience. It is a voice we should heed.Thank you. 
			</doc>
				<q  q_id="1" >
					<q_str>Where is considered the best place for studying climate change?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1'  correct="Yes">Antarctica</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >Wisconsin</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >Denver</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >Europe</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >Nevada</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="2" >
					<q_str>Why is ice important for studying climate change?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >because the average Earth temperature in the past can be measured</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >because desertification over time can be studied</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >because it contains fossil fuels from a million years ago</answer>
					<answer a_id='4'  correct="Yes">because it contains greenhouse gases from the past</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >because air purity over time can be measured</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="3" >
					<q_str>In which American state is located the laboratory which is distributing antarctic ice samples for analysis?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1'  correct="Yes">Colorado</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >California</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >Alaska</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >Texas</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >Massachusetts</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="4" >
					<q_str>In what country was an important decision about harmful ozone gases taken?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1'  correct="Yes">Canada</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >United States</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >China</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >Japan</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >Italy</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="5" >
					<q_str>Where is the Antarctic ice used for studying climate change obtained from?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >from mountains</answer>
					<answer a_id='2'  correct="Yes">drilling into the surface</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >the Antarctic sea</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >the air</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >the ozone layer</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="6" >
					<q_str>Where is the coldest place on Earth?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >the North Pole</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >the tropics</answer>
					<answer a_id='3'  correct="Yes">Antarctica</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >Montreal</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >Siberia</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="7" >
					<q_str>What other information important for climate change is stored in Antarctic ice?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >ozone gasses</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >a register of ocean currents</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >the amount of precipitation</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >crystals</answer>
					<answer a_id='5'  correct="Yes">measurements of the Earth's temperature</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="8" >
					<q_str>What consequence did the substitution of harmful ozone gases in the Montreal Protocol have?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >a reduction in the number of cooling devices</answer>
					<answer a_id='2'  correct="Yes">the use of more powerful greenhouse effect gases</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >a reduction in size of the ozone hole</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >an increase in the Earth's warming</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >a reduction in CO2 levels</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="9" >
					<q_str>Why is it so important to study the relation between greenhouse gases and climate change?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >to increase the emission of gases causing global warming</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >to increase the Earth's temperature</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >to threaten the quality of life</answer>
					<answer a_id='4'  correct="Yes">to have a better knowledge of both phenomena</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >to gain a better knowledge of politics</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="10" >
					<q_str>Why does Antarctic ice contain elements from the past?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >because wind brings materials to the Arctic</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >because the ozone layer is smaller over Antarctica</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >because the sea brings sediments</answer>
					<answer a_id='4'  correct="Yes">because materials brought by storms are stored in the snow</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >because of its aridity</answer>
				</q>
		</reading-test>
	</topic>
	<topic t_id="3" t_name="Music and society">
		<reading-test r_id="9">
			<doc d_id="9">
Adam Sadowsky engineers a viral music videoHi there. I'm going to be talking a little bit about music, machines and life. Or, more specifically, what we learned from the creation of a very large and complicated machine for a music video. Some of you may recognize this image. This is the opening frame of the video that we created. We'll be showing the video at the end, but before we do, I want to talk a little bit about what it is that they wanted.Now, when we first started talking to OK Go -- the name of the song is "This Too Shall Pass" -- we were really excited because they expressed interest in building a machine that they could dance with. And we were very excited about this because, of course, they have a history of dancing with machines. They're responsible for this video, "Here It Goes Again." 50-million-plus views on YouTube. Four guys dancing on treadmills, no cuts, just a static camera. A fantastically viral and wonderful video. So we were really excited about working with them. And we sort of started talking about what it is that they wanted. And they explained that they wanted kind of a Rube Goldberg machine.Now, for those of you who don't know, a Rube Goldberg machine is a complicated contraption, an incredibly over-engineered piece of machinery that accomplishes a relatively simple task. So we were excited by this idea, and we started talking about exactly what it would look like. And we came up with some parameters that -- you know, building a Rube Goldberg machine has limitations, but it also is pretty wide open.And we wanted to make sure that we did something that would work for a music video. So we came up with a list of requirements, the "10 commandments," and they were, in order of ascending difficulty: The first is "No magic." Everything that happened on screen had to be very easily understood by a typical viewer. The rule of thumb was that, if my mother couldn't understand it, then we couldn't use it in the video. They wanted band integration, that is the machine acting upon the band members, specifically not the other way around. They wanted the machine action to follow the song feeling. So as the song picks up emotion, so should the machine get grander in its process. They wanted us to make use of the space. So we have this 10,000 sq. ft. warehouse we were using, divided between two floors. It included an exterior loading dock. We used all of that, including a giant hole in the floor that we actually descended the camera and cameraman through. They wanted it messy, and we were happy to oblige. The machine itself would start the music. So the machine would get started, it would travel some distance, reacting along the way, hit play on an iPod or a tape deck or something that would start playback. And the machine would maintain synchronization throughout. And speaking of synchronization, they wanted it to sync to the rhythm and to hit specific beats along the way. Okay. (Laughter) They wanted it to end precisely on time. Okay, so now the start to finish timing has to be perfect. And they wanted the music to drop out at a certain point in the video and actual live audio from the machine to play part of the song. And as if that wasn't enough, all of these incredibly complicating things, right, they wanted it in one shot.(Laughter)(Applause)Okay. So, just some statistics about, sort of, what we went through in the process. The machine itself has 89 distinct interactions. It took us 85 takes to get it on film to our satisfaction. Of those 85 takes, only three actually successfully completed their run. We destroyed two pianos and 10 televisions in the process. We went to Home Depot well over a hundred times. (Laughter) And we lost one high-heeled shoe when one of our engineers, Heather Knight, left her high-heeled shoe -- after a nice dinner, and returned back to the build -- and left it in a pile of stuff. And another engineer thought, "Well, that would be a really good thing to use." And ended up using it as a really nice trigger. And it's actually in the machine.So what did we learn from all of this? Well, having completed this, we have the opportunity to step back and reflect on some of the things. And we learned that small stuff stinks. Little balls in wooden tracks are really susceptible to humidity and temperature and a little bit of dust, and they fall out of the tracks, the exact angles makes it hard to get right. And yet, a bowling ball will always follow the same path. It doesn't matter what temperature it is, doesn't matter what's in its way; it will pretty much get where it needs to go. But as much as the small stuff stinks, we needed somewhere to start, so that we would have somewhere to go. And so you have to start with it. You have to focus on it. Small stuff stinks, but, of course, it's essential, right.What else? Planning is incredibly important. (Laughter) You know, we spent a lot of time ideating and even building some of these things. It's been said that, "No battle plan survives contact with the enemy." I think our enemy was physics, (Laughter) and she's a cruel mistress. Often, we had to pull things out as a result because of timing or aesthetics or whatever. And so while planning is important, so is flexibility. These are all things that ended up not making it into the final machine. So also, put reliable stuff last, the stuff that's going to run every time. Again, small to large is relevant here. The little Lego car in the beginning of the video references the big, real car near the end of the video. The big, real car works every time; there's no problem about it. The little one had a tendency to try to run off the track and that's a problem. But you don't want to have to reset the whole machine because the Lego car at the end doesn't work, right. So you put that up front so that, if it fails, at least you know you don't have to reset the whole thing.Life can be messy. There were incredibly difficult moments in the building of this thing. Months were spent in this tiny, cold warehouse. And the wonderful elation that we had when we finally completed it. So it's important to remember that whether it's good or it's bad, "This Too Shall Pass."Thank you very much.
			</doc>
				<q  q_id="1" >
					<q_str>What is the overall subject of the talk?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1'  correct="Yes">making a music video</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >watching YouTube</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >maintaining synchronisation</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >studying Physics</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >planning a project</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="2" >
					<q_str>What is the name of the rock band who wanted a machine?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >YouTube</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >10 Commandments</answer>
					<answer a_id='3'  correct="Yes">OK Go</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >Heather Knight</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >Laughter</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="3" >
					<q_str>What did OK Go do previously in a video?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >they walked in a warehouse</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >they sang at the piano</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >they watched television</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >they ate a nice dinner</answer>
					<answer a_id='5'  correct="Yes">they danced on treadmills</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="4" >
					<q_str>How many times was OK Go's video viewed?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1'  correct="Yes">more than 50 million</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >fifty</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >a million</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >10,000</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >85</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="5" >
					<q_str>What is a Rube Goldberg machine?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >a simple system for performing a complicated operation</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >a song which picks up complex emotion</answer>
					<answer a_id='3'  correct="Yes">a complicated device for performing a simple operation</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >any machine containing gold</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >something watched on YouTube</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="6" >
					<q_str>How many keyboard instruments were broken?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1'  correct="Yes">two</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >10</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >85</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >89</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >a hundred</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="7" >
					<q_str>In the "10 commandments of music video", how was the action of the machine to follow the feeling of the song?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >when the song became slower, the machine was to become faster</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >when the action became grander, the song was to become slower</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >when the video became more popular, the song was expected to sell more copies</answer>
					<answer a_id='4'  correct="Yes">when the song became more emotional, the machine was to work on a larger scale</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >when the dancing was on treadmills, the machine was to work faster</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="8" >
					<q_str>In what sort of building was the film of the Rube Goldberg machine made?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1'  correct="Yes">warehouse</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >house</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >Home Depot</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >television shop</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >hotel</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="9" >
					<q_str>How many times was it necessary to film the machine?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1'  correct="Yes">85</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >89</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >two</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >ten</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >a hundred</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="10" >
					<q_str>Why did they put reliable machine components at the end and not at the beginning?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >cars have a tendency to go off the track</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >a big car in the video references a small car</answer>
					<answer a_id='3'  correct="Yes">if it fails, you do not have to reset the whole machine</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >a plan does not survive contact with the enemy</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >timing and aesthetics are very important</answer>
				</q>
		</reading-test>
		<reading-test r_id="10">
			<doc d_id="10">
Ben Cameron: The true power of the performing artsI am a cultural omnivore, one whose daily commute is made possible by attachment to an iPod, an iPod that contains Wagner and Mozart, pop diva Christina Aquilera, country singer Josh Turner, gangsta rap artist Kirk Franklin, concerti, symphonies and more and more. I'm a voracious reader, a reader who deals with Ian McEwan down to Stephanie Meyer. I have read the "Twilight" tetralogy. And one who lives for my home theater, a home theater where I devour DVDs, video-on-demand and a lot of television. For me, "Law and Order: SVU," Tine Fey and "30 Rock" and "Judge Judy" -- "The people are real, the cases are real, the rulings are final." Now, I'm convinced a lot of you probably share my passions, especially my passion for "Judge Judy," and you'd fight anybody who attempted to take her away from us, but I'm a little less convinced that you share the central passion of my life, a passion for the live professional performing arts, performing arts that represent the orchestral repertoire, yes, but jazz as well, modern dance, opera, theater and more and more and more.You know, frankly, it's a sector that many of us who work in the field worry is being endangered and possibly dismantled by technology. While we initially heralded the Internet as the fantastic new marketing device that was going to solve all our problems, we now realize that the Internet is, if anything, too effective in that regard. Depending on who you read, an arts organization, or an artist, who tries to attract the attention of a potential single ticket buyer, now competes with between three and 5,000 different marketing messages a typical citizen see every single day. We now know in fact that technology is our biggest competitor for leisure time. Five yeas ago, Gen-X'ers spent 20.7 hours online and TV, the majority on TV. Gen-Y'ers spent even more -- 23.8 hours, the majority online. And now, a typical university entering student arrives at college already having spent 20,000 hours online and an additional 10,000 hours playing video games, a stark reminder that we operate in a cultural context where video games now outsell music and movie recordings combined.Moreover, we're afraid that technology has altered our very assumptions of cultural consumption. Thanks to the Internet, we believe we can get anything we want whenever we want it, delivered to our own doorstep. We can shop at three in the morning or eight at night, ordering jeans tailor-made for our unique body-types. Expectations of personalization and customization that the live performing arts -- which have set curtain times, set venues, attendant inconveniences of travel, parking and the like -- simply cannot meet. And we're all acutely aware: what's it going to mean in the future when we ask someone to pay a hundred dollars for a symphony, opera or ballet ticket, when that cultural consumer is used to downloading on the internet 24 hours a day for 99 cents a song or for free? These are enormous questions for those of us who work in this terrain. But as particular as they feel to us, we know we're not alone.All of us are engaged in a seismic, fundamental realignment of culture and communications, a realignment that is shaking and decimating the newspaper industry, the magazine industry, the book and publishing industry and more. Saddled in the performing arts as we are, by antiquated union agreements that inhibit and often prohibit mechanical reproduction and streaming, locked into large facilities that were designed to ossify the ideal relationship between artist and audience most appropriate to the 19th century and locked into a business model dependent on high ticket revenues, where we charge exorbitant prices, many of us shudder in the wake of the collapse of Tower Records and ask ourselves, "Are we next?" Everyone I talk to in performing arts resonates to the words of Adrienne Rich, who, in "Dreams of a Common Language" wrote, "We are out in a country that has no language, no laws. Whatever we do together is pure invention. The maps they gave us are out of date by years." And for those of you who love the arts, aren't you glad you invited me here to brighten your day?(Laughter)(Applause)Now, rather than saying that we're on the brink of our own annihilation, I prefer to believe that we are engaged in a fundamental reformation, a reformation like the religious Reformation of the 16th century. The arts reformation, like the religious Reformation, is spurred in part by technology, with, indeed, the printing press really leading the charge on the religious Reformation. Both reformations were predicated on fractious discussion, internal self-doubt and massive realignment of antiquated business models. And at heart, both reformations, I think, were asking the questions: who's entitled to practice? How are they entitled to practice? And indeed, do we need anyone to intermediate for us in order to have an experience with a spiritual divine?Chris Anderson, someone I trust you all know, editor and chief of Wired magazine and author of "The Long Tail," really was the first, for me, to nail a lot of this. He wrote a long time ago, you know, thanks to the invention of the Internet, web technology, mini cams and more, the means of artistic production have been democratized for the first time in all of human history. In the 1930s, if any of you wanted to make a movie, you had to work for Warner Bros. or RKO because who could afford a movie set and lighting equipment and editing equipment and scoring and more? And now who in this room doesn't know a 14 year-old hard at work on her second, third, or fourth movie? (Laughter) Similarly, the means of artistic distribution have been democratized for the first time in human history. Again, in the '30s, Warner Bros., RKO did that for you. Now, go to YouTube, Facebook; you have worldwide distribution without leaving the privacy of your own bedroom.This double impact is occasioning a massive redefinition of the cultural market, a time when anyone is a potential author. Frankly, what we're seeing now in this environment is a massive time, when the entire world is changing, as we move from a time when audience numbers are plummeting. But the number of arts participants, people who write poetry, who sing songs, who perform in church choirs, is exploding beyond our wildest imaginations. This group, others have called the "pro ams," amateur artists doing work at a professional level. You see them on YouTube, in dance competitions, film festivals and more. They are radically expanding our notions of the potential of an aesthetic vocabulary, while they are challenging and undermining the cultural autonomy of our traditional institutions. Ultimately, we now live in a world defined, not by consumption, but by participation.But I want to be clear, just as the religious Reformation did not spell the end to the formal Church or to the priesthood, I believe that our artistic institutions will continue to have importance. They currently are the best opportunities for artists to have lives of economic dignity, not opulence, of dignity. And they are the places where artists who deserve and want to work at a certain scale of resources will find a home. But to view them as synonymous with the entirety of the arts community is, by far, too short-sighted. And indeed, while we've tended to polarize the amateur from the professional, the single most exciting development in the last five to 10 years has been the rise of the professional hybrid artist, the professional artist, who works, not primarily in the concert hall or on the stage, but most frequently around women's rights, or human rights, or on global warming issues or AIDS relief for more, not out of economic necessity, but out of a deep, organic conviction that the work that she, or he, is called to do cannot be accomplished in the traditional hermetic arts environment.Today's dance world is not defined solely by the Royal Winnipeg Ballet or the National Ballet of Canada, but by Liz Lerman's Dance Exchange, a multi-generational, professional dance company, whose dancers range in age from 18 to 82, and who work with genomic scientists to embody the DNA strand and with nuclear physicists at CERN. Today's professional theater community is defined, not only the Shaw and Stratford Festivals, but by the Cornerstone Theater of Los Angeles, a collective of artists that, after 9/11, brought together 10 different religious communities -- the Bahia, the Catholic, the Muslim, the Jewish, even the Native American and the gay and lesbian communities of faith, helping them create their own individual plays and one massive play, where they explored the differences in their faith and found commonality as an important first step toward cross-community healing. Today's performers, like Rhodessa Jones, work in women's prisons, helping women prisoners articulate the pain of incarceration, while today's playwrights and directors work with young gangs to find alternate channels to violence and more and more and more. And indeed, I think, rather than being annihilated, the performing arts are posed on the brink of a time when we will be more important than we have ever been.You know, we've said for a long time, we are critical to the health of the economic communities in your town. And absolutely. I hope you know that every dollar spent on a performing arts ticket in a community generates five to seven additional dollars for the local economy, dollars spent in restaurants or on parking, at the fabric stores where we buy fabric for costumes, the piano tuner who tunes the instruments and more. But the arts are going to be more important to economies as we go forward, especially in industries we can't even imagine yet, just as they have been central to the iPod and the computer game industries, which few, if any of us, come have foreseen 10 to 15 years ago. Business leadership will depend more and more on emotional intelligence, the ability to listen deeply, to have empathy, to articulate change, to motivate others -- the very capacities that the arts cultivate with every encounter.Especially now, as we all must confront the fallacy of a market-only orientation, uninformed by social conscience, we must seize and celebrate the power of the arts to shape our individual and national characters, and especially characters of the young people, who, all too often, are subjected bombardment of sensation, rather than digested experience. Ultimately, especially now, in this world, where we live in a context of regressive and onerous immigration laws, in reality TV that thrives on humiliation, and in a context of analysis, where the thing we hear most repeatedly, day-in, day-out in the United States, in every train station, every bus station, every plane station is, "Ladies and gentlemen, please report any suspicious behavior or suspicious individuals to the authorities nearest you," when all of these ways we are encouraged to view our fellow human being with hostility and fear and contempt and suspicion.The arts, whatever they do, whenever they call us together, invite us to look at our fellow human being with generosity and curiosity. God knows, if we ever needed that capacity in human history, we need it now. You know, we're bound together, not, I think, by technology, entertainment and design, but by common cause. We work to promote healthy vibrant societies, to ameliorate human suffering, to promote a more thoughtful, substantive, empathic world order.I salute all of you as activists in that quest and urge you to embrace and hold dear the arts in your work, whatever your purpose may be. I promise you the hand of the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation is stretched out in friendship for now and years to come. And I thank you for your kindness and your patience in listening to me this afternoon.Thank you, and godspeed.
			</doc>
				<q  q_id="1" >
					<q_str>How many instances of advertising does one see in a day?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >10,000</answer>
					<answer a_id='2'  correct="Yes">5,000</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >five</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >20.7</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >23.8</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="2" >
					<q_str>Name a form of publishing which is also threatened by the Internet.</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >towers</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >maps</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >jeans</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >curtains</answer>
					<answer a_id='5'  correct="Yes">newspapers</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="3" >
					<q_str>How much time has a student entering university already spent either online or playing games?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >20,000 hours</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >10,000 hours </answer>
					<answer a_id='3'  correct="Yes">30,000 hours </answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >20.7 hours</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >23.8 hours</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="4" >
					<q_str>What are two difficulties associated with attending a live performance?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >jeans and set curtain times</answer>
					<answer a_id='2'  correct="Yes">parking and set curtain times</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >internet and set curtain times</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >customisation and set curtain times</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >body types and set curtain times</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="5" >
					<q_str>Why is it hard to expect consumers to pay high prices for tickets?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1'  correct="Yes">because so much is available on the Internet</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >because it will happen in the future</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >because you must park your car</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >because you work in a terrain</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >because we are not alone</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="6" >
					<q_str>What does Rhodessa Jones do?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >helps genomic scientists</answer>
					<answer a_id='2'  correct="Yes">helps women in prison</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >helps singers</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >helps young gangs</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >helps playwrights</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="7" >
					<q_str>What can a fourteen-year-old girl do?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1'  correct="Yes">make a film</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >sing a song</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >write a book</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >play a DVD</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >paint a picture</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="8" >
					<q_str>What is described as "the central passion of my life"?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1'  correct="Yes">the performance of music, theatre and dance</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >more and more and more</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >an iPod</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >the daily commute</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >law and order</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="9" >
					<q_str>What are "pro ams"</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >professional performers working at an amateur level</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >people who have an aesthetic vocabulary</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >people who are attending film festivals and more</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >people who have the wildest imaginations</answer>
					<answer a_id='5'  correct="Yes">amateur performers working at a professional level</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="10" >
					<q_str>What is the threat to the performing arts?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >marketing</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >organisations</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >artists</answer>
					<answer a_id='4'  correct="Yes">technology</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >tickets</answer>
				</q>
		</reading-test>
		<reading-test r_id="11">
			<doc d_id="11">
David Byrne How architecture helped music evolveThis is the venue where I, as a young man, some of the music that I wrote was first performed. It was, remarkably, a pretty good sounding room. With all the uneven walls and all the crap everywhere, it actually sounded pretty good. This is a song that was recorded there. (Music) This is not Talking Heads, in the picture anyway. (Music: "A Clean Break (Let's Work)" by Talking Heads) So the nature of the room meant that words could be understood. The lyrics of the songs could be pretty much understood. The sound system was kind of decent. And there wasn't a lot of reverberation in the room. So the rhythms could be pretty intact too, pretty concise. Other places around the country had similar rooms. This is Tootsie's Orchid Lounge in Nashville. The music was in some ways different, but in structure and form, very much the same. The clientele behavior was very much the same too. And so the bands at Tootsie's or at CBGB's had to play loud enough -- the volume had to be loud enough to overcome people falling down, shouting out and doing whatever else they were doing.Since then, I've played other places that are much nicer. I've played the Disney Hall here and Carnegie Hall and places like that. And it's been very exciting. But I also noticed that sometimes the music that I had written, or was writing at the time, didn't sound all that great in some of those halls. We managed, but sometimes those halls didn't seem exactly suited to the music I was making or had made. So I asked myself: Do I write stuff for specific rooms? Do I have a place, a venue, in mind when I write? Is that a kind of model for creativity? Do we all make things with a venue, a context, in mind?Okay, Africa. (Music: "Wenlenga" / Various artists) Most of the popular music that we know now has a big part of its roots in West Africa. And the music there, I would say, the instruments, the intricate rhythms, the way it's played, the setting, the context, it's all perfect. It all works perfect. The music works perfectly in that setting. There's no big room to create reverberation and confuse the rhythms. The instruments are loud enough that they can be heard without amplification, etc., etc. It's no accident. It's perfect for that particular context. And it would be a mess in a context like this. This is a gothic cathedral. (Music: "Spem In Alium" by Thomas Tallis) In a gothic cathedral, this kind of music is perfect. It doesn't change key. The notes are long. There's almost no rhythm whatsoever. And the room flatters the music. It actually improves it. This is the room that Bach wrote some of his music for. This is the organ. It's not as big as a gothic cathedral, so he can write things that are a little bit more intricate. He can, very innovatively, actually change keys without risking huge dissonances. (Music: "Fantasia On Jesu, Mein Freunde" by Johann S. Bach)This is a little bit later. This is the kind of rooms that Mozart wrote in. I think we're in like 1770, somewhere around there. They're smaller, even less reverberant, so he can write really frilly music that's very intricate -- and it works. (Music: "Sonata in F," KV 13, by Wolfgang A. Mozart) It fits the room perfectly. This is La Scala. It's from around the same time. I think it was built around 1776. People in the audience in these opera houses, when they were built, they used to yell out to one another. They used to eat, drink and yell out to people on the stage, just like they do at CBGB's and places like that. If they liked an aria, they would holler and suggest that it be done again as an encore, not at the end of the show, but immediately. (Laughter) And well, that was an opera experience. This is the opera house that Wagner built for himself. And the size of the room is not that big. It's smaller than this. But, Wagner made an innovation. He wanted a bigger band. He wanted a little more bombast. So he increased the size of the orchestra pit so he could get more low-end instruments in there. (Music: "Lohengrin / Prelude to Act III" by Richard Wagner)Okay. This is Carnegie Hall. Obviously, this kind of thing became popular. The halls got bigger. Carnegie Hall's fair-sized. It's larger than some of the other symphony halls. And they're a lot more reverberant than La Scala. Around the same, according to Alex Ross who writes for the New Yorker, this kind of rule came into effect that audiences had to be quiet, no more eating, drinking and yelling at the stage, or gossiping with one another during the show. They had to be very quiet. So those two things combined meant that a different kind of music worked best in these kind of halls. It meant that there could be extreme dynamics, which there weren't in some of these other kinds of music. Quiet parts could be heard that would have been drowned out by all the gossiping and shouting. But because of the reverberation in those rooms like Carnegie Hall, the music had to be maybe a little less rhythmic and a little more textural. (Music: "Symphony No. 8 in E Flat Major" by Gustav Mahler) This is Mahler. It looks like Bob Dylan, but it's Mahler. That was Bob's last record, yeah.(Laughter)Popular music, coming along at the same time. This is a jazz band. According to Scott Joplin, the bands were playing on riverboats and clubs. Again, it's noisy. They're playing for dancers. There's certain sections of the song -- the songs had different sections that the dancers really liked. And they'd say, "Play that part again." Well, there's only so many times you can play the same section of a song over and over again for the dancers. So the bands started to improvise new melodies. And a new form of music was born. (Music: "Royal Garden Blues" by W.C. Handy / Ethel Waters) These are played mainly in small rooms. People are dancing, shouting and drinking. So the music has to be loud enough to be heard above that. Same thing goes true for -- that's the beginning of the century -- for the whole of 20th-century popular music, whether it's rock or Latin music or whatever. [Live music] doesn't really change that much.It changes about a third of the way into the twentieth century, when this became one of the primary venues for music. And this was one way that the music got there. Microphones enabled singers, in particular, and musicians and composers, to completely change the kind of music that they were writing. So far, a lot of the stuff that was on the radio was live music, but singers, like Frank Sinatra, could use the mic and do things that they could never do without a microphone. Other singers after him, went even further. (Music: "My Funny Valentine" by Chet Baker) This is Chet Baker. And this kind of thing would have been impossible without a microphone. It would have been impossible without recorded music as well. And he's singing right into your ear. He's whispering into your ear. The effect is just electric. It's like the guy is sitting next to you, whispering who knows what into your ear.So at this point, music diverged. There's live music, and there's recorded music. And they no longer have to be exactly the same. Now there's venues like this, a discotheque, and there's jukeboxes in bars, where you don't even need to have a band. There doesn't need to be any live performing musicians whatsoever. And the sound systems are good. People began to make music specifically for discos and for those sound systems. And, as with jazz, the dancers liked certain sections more than they did others. So there early hip-hop guys would loop certain sections. (Music: "Rapper's Delight" by The Sugarhill Gang) The MC would improvise lyrics in the same way that the jazz players would improvise melodies. And another new form of music was born.Live performance, when it was incredibly successful, ended up in what is probably, acoustically, the worst sounding venues on the planet, sports stadiums, basketball arenas and hockey arenas. Musicians who ended up there did the best they could. They wrote what is now called arena rock, which is medium-speed ballads. (Music: "I Still Haven't Found What I'm Looking For" by U2) They did the best they could given that this is what they're writing for. The tempos are medium. It sounds big. It's more a social situation than a musical situation. And in some ways, the music that they're writing for this place works perfectly.So there's more new venues. One of the new ones is the automobile. I grew up with a radio in a car. But now that's evolved into something else. The car is a whole venue. (Music: "Who U Wit" by Lil' Jon &amp; the East Side Boyz) The music that, I would say, is written for automobile sound systems, works perfectly on it. It might not be what you want to listen to at home, but it works great in the car -- has a huge frequency spectrum, you know, big bass and high-end and the voice kind of stuck in the middle. Automobile music, you can share with your friends.There's one other kind of new venue, the private MP3 player. Presumably, this is just for Christian music. (Laughter) And in some ways it's like Carnegie Hall, or when the audience had to hush up, because you can now hear every single detail. In other ways, it's more like the West African music because if the music in an MP3 player gets too quiet, you turn it up, and the next minute, your ears are blasted out by a louder passage. So that doesn't really work. I think pop music, mainly, it's written today, to some extent, is written for these kind of players, for this kind of personal experience where you can hear extreme detail, but the dynamic doesn't change that much.So I asked myself: Okay, is this a model for creation, this adaptation that we do? And does it happen anywhere else? Well, according to David Attenborough and some other people, birds do it too. That the birds in the canopy, where the foliage is dense, their calls tend to be high-pitched, short and repetitive. And the birds on the floor tend to have lower pitched calls, so they don't get distorted when they bounce off the forest floor. And birds like this Savannah sparrow, they tend to have a buzzing (Sound clip: Savannah sparrow song) type call. And it turns out that a sound like this is the most energy efficient and practical way to transmit their call across the fields and savannahs. Other birds, like this tananger, have adapted within the same species. The tananger on the east coast of the United States, where the forests are a little denser, has one kind of call, and the tananger on the other side, on the west, (Sound clip: Scarlet tanager song) has a different kind of call. (Sound clip: Scarlet tanager song) So birds do it too.And I thought: Well, if this is a model for creation, if we make music, primarily the form at least, to fit these contexts, and if we make art to fit gallery walls or museum walls, and if we write software to fit existing operating systems, is that how it works? Yeah. I think it's evolutionary. It's adaptive. But the pleasure and the passion and the joy is still there. This is a reverse view of things from the kind of traditional romantic view. The romantic view is that first comes the passion and then the outpouring of emotion, and then somehow it gets shaped into something. And I'm saying, well, the passion's still there, but the vessel that it's going to be injected into and poured into, that is instinctively and intuitively created first. We already know where that passion is going. But this conflict of views is kind of interesting.The writer, Thomas Frank, says that this might be a kind of explanation why some voters vote against their best interests, that voters, like a lot of us, assume, that if they hear something that sounds like it's sincere, that it's coming from the gut, that it's passionate, that it's more authentic. And they'll vote for that. So that, if somebody can fake sincerity, if they can fake passion, they stand a better chance of being selected in that way, which seems a little dangerous. I'm saying the two, the passion, the joy, are not mutually exclusive.Maybe what the world needs now is for us to realize that we are like the birds. We adapt. We sing. And like the birds, the joy is still there, even though we have changed what we do to fit the context.Thank you very much.(Applause)
			</doc>
				<q  q_id="1" >
					<q_str>Why was it a good thing that there was minimal reverberation in the original Talking Heads venue?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1'  correct="Yes">you could understand the words</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >you could see the performers</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >you could enjoy the performance</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >you could observe the uneven walls</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >you could work harder</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="2" >
					<q_str>Name an American concert hall.</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >Talking Heads</answer>
					<answer a_id='2'  correct="Yes">Disney Hall</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >Wenlenga</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >La Scala</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >Royal Garden Blues</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="3" >
					<q_str>Why can Bach change key without risking dissonances?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >the room had an organ</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >there was no rhythm</answer>
					<answer a_id='3'  correct="Yes">the room was smaller</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >the room was larger</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >the music was perfect</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="4" >
					<q_str>Why did the Bayreuth Festspielhaus have a large orchestra pit?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >to eat, drink and yell out</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >to be more intricate</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >to help Mozart</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >to suggest an encore</answer>
					<answer a_id='5'  correct="Yes">to accommodate low-end instruments</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="5" >
					<q_str>What was the paradox of success associated with arena rock music?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >medium-speed ballads were played very quickly</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >musicians found themseleves in a social situation</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >hockey matches were played in basketball stadiums</answer>
					<answer a_id='4'  correct="Yes">the best bands ended up playing in the worst venues</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >basketball was played in large arenas</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="6" >
					<q_str>Which of the following are considered new musical "venues"?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1'  correct="Yes">the car and the MP3 player</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >the car and the Carnegie Hall</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >the Carnegie Hall and the MP3 player</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >high-end music and the car</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >west African Music and the MP3 player</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="7" >
					<q_str>In what two ways are people like birds?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1'  correct="Yes">they adapt and sing</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >they adapt and dance</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >they walk and sing</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >they walk and dance</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >they fish and walk</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="8" >
					<q_str>What was made possible in music when audiences were forced to be quiet?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >Bob Dylan's last record</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >gossiping and shouting at all times</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >articles in the New Yorker by Alex Ross</answer>
					<answer a_id='4'  correct="Yes">extreme dynamics</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >the music of Scott Joplin</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="9" >
					<q_str>What technological development enabled composers to write a new kind of music?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >singers</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >venues</answer>
					<answer a_id='3'  correct="Yes">microphones</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >things</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >changes</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="10" >
					<q_str>When music diverged, what were the two paths?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >live music and jazz</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >discos and sound systems</answer>
					<answer a_id='3'  correct="Yes">live music and recorded music</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >jukeboxes and bars</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >jazz and recorded music</answer>
				</q>
		</reading-test>
		<reading-test r_id="12">
			<doc d_id="12">
Jose Abreu on kids transformed by musicChris Anderson: Let's now see the extraordinary speech that we captured a couple weeks ago.(Music)Jose Antonio Abreu: My dear friends, ladies and gentlemen, I am overjoyed today at being awarded the TED Prize on behalf of all the distinguished music teachers, artists and educators from Venezuela who have selflessly and loyally accompanied me for 35 years in founding, growing and developing in Venezuela the National System of Youth and Children's Orchestras and Choirs.Since I was a boy, in my early childhood, I always wanted to be a musician, and, thank God, I made it. From my teachers, my family and my community, I had all the necessary support to become a musician. All my life I've dreamed that all Venezuelan children have the same opportunity that I had. From that desire and from my heart stemmed the idea to make music a deep and global reality for my country.From the very first rehearsal, I saw the bright future ahead. Because the rehearsal meant a great challenge to me. I had received a donation of 50 music stands to be used by 100 boys in that rehearsal. When I arrived at the rehearsal, only 11 kids had shown up, and I said to myself, "Do I close the program or multiply these kids?" I decided to face the challenge, and on that same night, I promised those 11 children I'd turn our orchestra into one of the leading orchestras in the world. Two months ago, I remembered that promise I made, when a distinguished English critic published an article in the London Times, asking who could be the winner of the Orchestra World Cup. He mentioned four great world orchestras, and the fifth one was Venezuela's Youth Symphony Orchestra. Today we can say that art in Latin America is no longer a monopoly of elites and that it has become a social right, a right for all the people.Child: There is no difference here between classes, nor white or black, if you have money or not. Simply, if you are talented, if you have the vocation and the will to be here you get in, you share with us and make music.JA: During the recent tour by the Simon Bolivar Youth Orchestra of Venezuela of U.S. and Europe we saw how our music moved young audiences to the bottom of their souls, how children and adolescents rushed up to the stage to receive the jackets from our musicians, how the standing ovations, sometimes 30 minutes long, seemed to last forever, and how the public, after the concert was over, went out into the street to greet our young people in triumph. This meant not only an artistic triumph, but also a profound emotional sympathy between the public of the most advanced nations of the world and the musical youth of Latin America, as seen in Venezuela, giving these audiences a message of music, vitality, energy, enthusiasm and strength.In its essence, the orchestra and the choir are much more than artistic structures. They are examples and schools of social life, because to sing and to play together means to intimately coexist toward perfection and excellence, following a strict discipline of organization and coordination in order to seek the harmonic interdependence of voices and instruments. That's how they build a spirit of solidarity and fraternity among them, develop their self-esteem and foster the ethical and aesthetical values related to the music in all its senses. This is why music is immensely important in the awakening of sensibility, in the forging of values and in the training of youngsters to teach other kids.Child: After all this time here, music is life. Nothing else. Music is life.JA: Each teenager and child in El Sistema has his own story, and they are all important and of great significance to me. Let me mention the case of Edicson Ruiz. He is a boy from a parish in Caracas who passionately attended to his double bass lessons at the San Agustin's Junior Orchestra. With his effort, and the support of his mother, his family and his community, he became a principal member in the double bass segment of the Berlin Philharmonic Orchestra. We have another well-known case -- Gustavo Dudamel. He started as a boy member of the children's orchestra in his hometown, Barquisimeto. There, he grew as a violinist and as a conductor. He became the conductor of Venezuela's junior orchestras, and today conducts the world's greatest orchestras. He is the musical director of Los Angeles Philharmonic, and is still the overall leader of Venezuela's junior orchestras. He was the conductor of the Gothenburg Symphony Orchestra, and he's an unbeatable example for young musicians in Latin America and the world.The structure of El Sistema is based on a new and flexible managing style adapted to the features of each community and region, and today attends to 300,000 children of the lower and middle class all over Venezuela. It's a program of social rescue and deep cultural transformation designed to the whole Venezuelan society with absolutely no distinctions whatsoever, but emphasizing on the vulnerable and endangered social groups.The effect of El Sistema is felt in three fundamental circles -- in the personal/social circle, in the family circle and in the community. In the personal/social circle, the children in the orchestras and choirs develop their intellectual and emotional side. The music becomes a source for developing the dimensions of the human being, thus elevating the spirit and leading man to a full development of his personality. So, the emotional and intellectual profits are huge -- the acquisition of leadership, teaching and training principles, the sense of commitment, responsibility, generosity and dedication to others, and the individual contribution to achieve great collective goals. All this leads to the development of self-esteem and confidence.Mother Teresa of Calcutta insisted on something that always impressed me -- the most miserable and tragic thing about poverty is not the lack of bread or roof, but the feeling of being no-one, the feeling of not being anyone, the lack of identification, the lack of public esteem. That's why the child's development in the orchestra and the choir provides him with a noble identity and makes him a role model for his family and community. It makes him a better student at school because it inspires in him a sense of responsibility, perseverance and punctuality that will greatly help him at school.Within the family, the parents' support is unconditional. The child becomes a role model for both his parents, and this is very important for a poor child. Once the child discovers he is important for his family, he begins to seek new ways of improving himself and hopes better for himself and his community. Also, he hopes for social and economic improvements for his own family. All this makes up a constructive and ascending social dynamic. The large majority of our children belong, as I already mentioned, to the most vulnerable strata of the Venezuelan population. That encourages them to embrace new dreams, new goals, and progress in the various opportunities that music has to offer.Finally, in the circle of the community, the orchestras prove to be the creative spaces of culture and sources of exchange and new meanings. The spontaneity music has excludes it as a luxury item and makes it a patrimony of society. It's what makes a child play a violin at home, while his father works in his carpentry. It's what makes a little girl play the clarinet at home, while her mother does the housework. The idea is that the families join with pride and joy in the activities of the orchestras and the choirs their children belong to. The huge spiritual world that music produces in itself, which also lies within itself, ends up overcoming material poverty. From the minute a child's taught how to play an instrument, he's no longer poor. He becomes a child in progress heading for a professional level, who'll later become a full citizen. Needless to say that music is the number one prevention against prostitution, violence, bad habits, and everything degrading in the life of a child.A few years ago, historian Arnold Toynbee said that the world was suffering a huge spiritual crisis. Not an economic or social crisis, but a spiritual one. I believe that to confront such a crisis, only art and religion can give proper answers to humanity, to mankind's deepest aspirations, and to the historic demands of our times. Education being the synthesis of wisdom and knowledge, it's the means to strive for a more perfect, more aware more noble and more just society.With passion and enthusiasm we pay profound respects to TED for its outstanding humanism, the scope of its principles, for its open and generous promotion of young values. We hope that TED can contribute in a full and fundamental way to the building of this new era in the teaching of music, in which the social, communal, spiritual and vindicatory aims of the child and the adolescent become a beacon and a goal for a vast social mission. No longer putting society at the service of art, and much less at the services of monopolies of the elite, but instead art at the service of society, at the service of the weakest, at the service of the children, at the service of the sick, at the service of the vulnerable, and at the service of all those who cry for vindication through the spirit of their human condition and the raising up of their dignity.(Music)(Applause)CA: We are going live now to Caracas. We are going live to Caracas to hear Maestro Abreu's TED Prize wish.JA: Here is my TED Prize wish -- I wish that you help to create and document a special training program for 50 gifted young musicians passionate about their art and social justice and dedicated to bringing El Sistema to the United States and other countries. Thank you very much.(Applause)
			</doc>
				<q  q_id="1" >
					<q_str>What is the full name of El Sistema?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1'  correct="Yes">The National System of Youth and Children's Orchestras and Choirs</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >Venezuela's Youth Symphony Orchestra</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >Simon Bolivar Youth Orchestra of Venezuela</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >Arnold Toynbee</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >Mother Teresa of Calcutta</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="2" >
					<q_str>How many children attended the first rehearsal?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >30</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >50</answer>
					<answer a_id='3'  correct="Yes">11</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >100</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >35</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="3" >
					<q_str>How many orchestras were mentioned in the London Times?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >one</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >35</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >six</answer>
					<answer a_id='4'  correct="Yes">five</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >11</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="4" >
					<q_str>For how long did people applaud at performances of the Bolivar Youth Orchestra?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >two minutes</answer>
					<answer a_id='2'  correct="Yes">thirty minutes</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >eleven minutes</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >five minutes</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >one minute</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="5" >
					<q_str>Name two participants in El Sistema who are associated with famous orchestras.</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >Barquisimeto and Gustavo Dudamel</answer>
					<answer a_id='2'  correct="Yes">Edicson Ruiz and Gustavo Dudamel</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >Caracas and Edicson Ruiz</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >Caracas and Barquisimeto</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >San Agustin and Venezuela</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="6" >
					<q_str>What is the worst thing about being poor?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >the enjoyment of music</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >the satisfaction of playing</answer>
					<answer a_id='3'  correct="Yes">the feeling of being no-one</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >the lack of food</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >the lack of shelter</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="7" >
					<q_str>Give an example of the way in which music is no longer a luxury but a basic component of society.</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1'  correct="Yes">a child plays a violin at home</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >a father works at his carpentry</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >a mother does the housework</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >a boy plays football</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >an aunt reads a book</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="8" >
					<q_str>Which person born in 1889 said that the world was in a crisis?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >Mother Teresa</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >Edicson Ruiz</answer>
					<answer a_id='3'  correct="Yes">Arnold Toynbee</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >Gustavo Dudamel</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >Chris Anderson</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="9" >
					<q_str>How long has EL Sistema been operating?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >a few years</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >50 years</answer>
					<answer a_id='3'  correct="Yes">35 years</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >one year</answer>
					<answer a_id='5' >one day</answer>
				</q>
				<q  q_id="10" >
					<q_str>What is the main idea behind El Sistema?</q_str>
					<answer a_id='1' >to play music in Barquisimeto</answer>
					<answer a_id='2' >to be awarded a prize by TED</answer>
					<answer a_id='3' >to receive a standing ovation</answer>
					<answer a_id='4' >to visit a parish in Caracas</answer>
					<answer a_id='5'  correct="Yes">to make music a deep and global reality</answer>
				</q>
		</reading-test>
	</topic>
</test-set>